Hey, yo, yo, pack the chrome stuff by like mrs.
Jones, liverpool, mathematics.
We have the devil spoken stone,
upward heads to bed,
make shots and reference bed with the church guys.
Sorry, for not be in pittsburgh, as I said,
I had come out here to seattle.
I'm actually in front of the courthouse right now,
because smooth shoes,
boy three fingers and this guy has used the goose.
They got popped last year for passing bad checks.
And so they asked me to come in a as a character witness for them.
It's not looking good in there for them.
That's their problem, not mine.
So I figured, let's come out here and do the class lecture.
Let's talk about databases.
For today's class, we're going to be talking about.
Sort of is that an overview of what with these sort of modern query engines
or these modern lap database
systems look like at a high level,
that'll then set us up for how we progress through the various topics
throughout the rest of the semester.
This is a high level outline of where we're going in this course.
And I didn't want to bring this up last class,
because I want to spend time talking about the sort of historical overview
of the standard databases.
And so to understand why we're at the point where today we're focusing
on the relational database systems,
but this is a high level architecture of the roadmap of how to build
a modern o lab database system.
We're going to first talk about storage.
Essentially, how do we actually going to represent data on disk?
Compress it?
Maybe build some indexes that we can use for accelerating query execution.
And then we'll use all that storage ideas about how we want to store the datas.
Then spend most of time discussing how we actually want to execute queries
on this data.
We'll talk about processing models how to schedule queries.
The task within them.
We'll spend a lot of time talking about how to do vector rise execution.
Taking advantage of cindy query compilation will be another major theme or method.
We can use to speed things up.
We'll spend a lot of time talking about different joint algorithms.
And something new that we'll discuss this year that I haven't discussed
in previous years is materialized views.
And I have to make fully materialized views is actually something I know,
the least about in database systems.
So we'll spend some time on this.
And then we'll talk about query optimization.
How do you take a query plan?
Convert it into to single query, generate the query plan,
how to design sort of modern network interfaces.
And then the rest of the semester after that,
will be doing an analysis and deep introspection into real systems
like the snowflake system.
You guys read today's paper,
but also a big query spark and a bunch of other modern systems.
This this sort of layer diagram showing here is very similar to what we
discussed in the intro class,
where it's essentially the system for going from the bottom up.
You're gonna build these different abstraction interfaces.
And they'll have,
you'll expose an api that we then integrate with into the layer above it.
And then to the nbn we end up with the client interface will be exposed
to the application.
This going for the next three lectures for lectures or so,
we'll focus on the storage lab.
That'll then define how we actually want to when api will have exposed
to us when we want to run queries.
Today's execution, as I said,
this is a high level overview of what of what modern overlap systems look like.
So we're not going to go too deep.
And like, what are the algorithms you do?
Fixing queries that also come later?
This class isn't necessarily about distributed databases,
because I want to spend time discussing what are the modern techniques
of what you do on a single node to process data?
And then we'll layer on top of that the distributed architecture,
but it's good to understand a little bit of what these what it
should be said would look like for a modern outlet system.
So understand the big fish were gone,
but it really has been the said before and many other classes.
We need to get the single node system to be high performance
and super optimized first.
Before we make it distributed,
just like making a database distributed,
isn't this magic wand or magic solution?
That solves all the scalable skillet problems?
Like if you have a crappy single node system making distributed as means
you have a multi node crappy system.
We need to kneel that down first.
And I want to spend a little time talking at the end
about this bigger trend about the the commodization of the components
of these o lab systems.
So we're mostly talking about systems like snowflake and spark,
where they're these monolithic systems that are all where the vendor
has implemented all the bits and pieces of them.
But there is a trend now where people are trying to build sort
of stand alone pieces of actually the layer diagram I showed before.
And in theory,
one could then tie these put these things together.
At later point, I hope that new whole lab system,
but we're not entirely there yet,
but i'll talk about some early,
some early work in this space.
The first thing I understand what does distributed query what the execution
distributed query look like in a
what does an oled query look like in a distributed database system?
And I will say at a high level,
it's essentially the same as you would have in a single system.
Right?
Sql query shows up the you run through the parser,
the binder, the optimizer, and so forth.
It'll generate a directed acyclic graph of physical operators,
where you have these physical operators scan and join implementation.
And they're taking some input coming from its children operators,
doing some amount of computation on them,
and then passing that along to the to its parent operator.
And so the fact that these operators may be excluded across multiple nodes
versus all running on the single box,
single node.
At a higher there, again,
there really isn't any difference.
There's the orchestration of the task and so forth,
but that's sort of outside the scope of what
we're talking about right here today.
Like the day, there's a query plan.
We break it up into task,
redistribute across nodes.
It's no different than taking a query plan,
breaking up the task and distribute across cores on a a multi cpu box,
all the operators that we had before, one of the single no system,
cable scans, joints, and aggregation sorting.
All these exist in an initiative system.
At a high level, it's gonna look at this, right?
Say there's gonna be some notion of a worker node.
And worker is going to have acpu it's going to have local memory.
It's going to have local disk.
And and say,
if we go from sort of left to right in the diagram here,
we're trying to execute a query.
The each of these nodes are responsible for taking some input in doing
some computation for the operator that they've been assigned
for a given task,
and then producing output as results that then either goes
back to the client or goes off to the next worker notes.
Say we start in the very beginning,
say this is the bottom of query plan and we want to read what we call
persistent data.
The persistent data is going to be the the underlying two poles
of the tables that are defined in the database.
These going to be some files that are going to have data that we know
how to interpret their types based on some scheme information,
a catalog.
We know how to access it and scan and do something, right?
I'm not showing this diagram whether the persistent data is
local to the worker node,
or it's some shared disk architecture or object store,
which will cover it a second.
It for our purposes here doesn't matter.
Again, we take in the persistent data,
we're doing some kind of scan,
and we're going to boost some amount of intermediate data.
And then when you now should need to ship this intermediate data
to the sort of the next stage of the query plan,
which either could be on the same node or a different node.
One of the ways we can do this is through what is called a shuffle operation.
Where after we do some operator,
we would pass along this intermediate data to another set of nodes that
are going to distribute the the results based
on some hash key or some range partitioning.
And then there will be some other workers that can then pull that data
from the shuffle notes.
Now, i'm putting the shuffle node phase as optional here,
because I don't think snowflake does this with explicit notes, but big,
gray and drummer do this.
The ideas like these in memory nodes that are have the shuffle notes,
have a lot of memory.
And so they try to keep everything at cache without smoking a desk.
And it's a way to sort of redistribute things.
I'm also showing here there's a sort of 1 to 1 correspondence
between number shuffle nodes and worker nodes
doesn't necessarily need to be the case you could fan out or fan
in at this different stage.
But it's just way to get the intermediate data from the previous stage
to the next stage.
And if necessary redistributed on some new partition game,
then this network or node does additional computations.
It has more intermediate data.
They say the trouble phase or not doesn't matter.
But they say, now it descends into this other worker node,
who then does some file final aggregation of coalescing of the data
to produce the result of the application?
Again,
there's nothing true,
drastically,
dramatically different than how we'd execute a query on attribute system
versus a single node system.
We just may have to do spend more time doing data movement which
nowadays is actually not as bad as it used to be that
the hierarchy was that the the network going with the network was
the slowest and reading from this is the slowest and the memory,
but never gotten really fast now.
Especially in the case of big grade, they have accelerated.
You have hard acceleration for these fish shuffle operation.
In some cases,
it's actually faster to send things for the network than read from disk.
This shuffle phase was a big deal.
But the main thing I want to expose here is this idea of the notion
of persistent data,
intermediate data,
because that's going to depend on or that.
What we actually do with the different types of data is going to depend
on what the architecture of whether to share nothing to share disk system.
This taxonomy between persistent data and intermediate data comes
from the significant paper that you guys read.
What they would call it persistent data is the data that's called a source
of record for the database.
If I inserted to pull part of it,
bulk, loading some data or copying or insert operation.
The I expect that two would reside in these persistent files
in the persistent data.
In a modern system,
we're gonna assume that the persistent data of the files of persistent data
is immutable.
And that's a dramatic change from how people designed assumed data systems
were built from the years past,
because you assume you're running with a local disk that you
can read and write as it as needed.
But in a modern cloud setting,
we are running on an object store,
or even if you're running on the early predecessor,
like hgfs those file systems were,
some of them were append only,
but you couldn't do in place updates.
So in the case of a modern lab system,
they're gonna assume that these files are immutable.
And he put you to support updating them and you have to maintain somebody
to keep track of how whether something is,
whether a version of a tube has been overwritten by a newer version of.
But we'll come to that.
We'll talk about more of that next class.
And then the other interesting part effect is going to be these,
what they would be called intermediate data.
And this is the output of the operators that we execute in a query plan
that we then need to send along to the next operator in the query plan.
This actually can be a lot of data.
And in the sense of paper,
they talk about how the amount of intermediate data that a query
would generate has no little to no correlation to the amount
of data persistent data reading.
Being like the table can be really, really small,
but then they still end up producing a lot of intermediate data
because of some computation that they're doing,
or could also be, it's not correlated to the execution time.
So if a query takes a long time to run,
that doesn't necessarily mean they have to generate a lot of intermediate data.
This animated data is interesting because it's it's you need to move
along as fast as possible,
but you don't need necessarily need to worry about durability,
fault tolerance in persisting it.
Because as soon as you finish the query,
the next stage going from up to the next immediately throw it away.
Right?
So that the paper talks about how this sort of trade off between deciding
what the spelling disk processing data,
intermediate data.
And it was often the case you wanna keep intermediate data in memory as you
move it along.
So we need to talk about what the sort of system architecture would look
like in a modern outlap system.
And there's a couple ways to think about this is, but the end of the day,
there's how it's going to move data.
There are mood persistent data to or to start beginning the execution
on the persistent data,
like start scanning it.
And it will determine also where it's located.
Again, in the interclass,
we talk about this sort of shared nothing and shared disk or just push
the query the data,
pull data, the query.
We talk of these things as being very these music exclusive,
but it's actually not the case,
especially in a modern platforms where systems don't clean divide
along these lines.
They actually do a little bit of everything.
We can understand the tradeoffs and the applications of these approaches.
The first thing is to say, again,
if we want to start reading processing data,
how should we begin that process?
And then as we move from one stage,
the next we have two operators.
How do we transfer?
Or what do we transfer for the intermediate results?
First,
just talking about how do we begin the execution of things
or or the movement of data.
The two choices, again,
are pushing the query to the data or pulling the data, the query.
Again, these ideas aren't new.
They go back to a lot of the work that was done in the late 80s, early 90s,
and some of the first like parallel distributed data system architectures.
And the tradeoffs of how to understand these things, I think,
of change in modern times,
just because of honestly,
how much harbor has gotten better,
especially the the proliferation of cloud services,
like object stores where maybe things in the past like shared nothing
and was the dominant architecture that we would assume that was
the best approach.
And you see, it was always logical,
always out to push the data, the query,
to push the computation where the data is located.
But now that's not always the case in the cloud.
The first thing is, again,
how we want to initiate the process of executing portions of a query
on a database or on data.
The first approach is you pushing the query to the data.
And this means that we want to move as much computation as we can to
the location of where data is located.
The thought process here is that the cost of executing some
portion of a query where the data is located was always gonna be
much cheaper than the cost of transferring the data
to some other compute node.
Again, think about it.
I have a disk.
On one node, I have a computation another.
I'd rather send the query to the data where on the disk has the disk
where it's located,
then have to transfer it out.
Because the network, the net cost is so high.
The alternative is to pull the data of the query.
This is where you are,
where the query is.
You leave it at that computational resource,
and then the data needs access to the operator,
the data that needs opportunities access.
You transferred over to that node.
This could be necessary in a situation where you can't run any queries.
You can't do any computation where the day is located.
If I have aa remote file system where I can't run anything,
I I can only do gets and sets and delete,
you'd have to do pull data the query.
As I said,
the harbor has gotten much better in recent years where this isn't
always the best design choice upholding the query because now again,
the network on in cloud systems is pretty fat.
The other interesting also, too,
is saying these are always usually exclusive anymore because there are
some there are some cloud object
stores where you can actually push some computation to to the data,
even though you wouldn't think you would be able to do it.
So on s three,
they have this select operator select operation,
where you can do something that sort of looks like pseudo sequel.
So where clause and you can send that to as an s three command to do
some initial filtering directly in s three,
so that you're only now trenching the data that would satisfy your wear clothes.
So again, the idea is that I do a select state,
but I can maybe send portion of the where clause to s three,
s three knows how to negatively understand csv file,
jason or public files,
and then do that filter and only send back the results that within the rows
that satisfy it.
That's actually pretty powerful now,
because that's basically pushing the data query,
but not all of the query,
but at least enough where you could do get a big way in doing some filtering.
Am amazon?
Sorry,
microsoft azure blob storage has something pretty similar where you can do.
You can do something again that looks like sequel to do some initial filtering.
I don't know what file formats they support,
but the basic idea is the same thing.
So again, just going forward were or gonna be using pool query,
pool data to the query for the lower portions of the query plan,
like the access methods of scanning the tables.
But then we're probably gonna really push the,
but and as we go from the intermediate phases,
it's also probably pushing data query as well.
Now we want to talk about the two high level approaches
for better distributed system.
Again, these aren't.
This one is actually pretty,
this is pretty rigid or how this is a clean dichotomy for systems.
Today's.
But the the first type of architecture is the more traditional.
One people think of distributed systems is a shared nothing system.
This is actually aa phrase or term coined by mike stern breaker going
back to like the 1980s.
And again,
the idea here was this was presumed to be the better way to build
distributed data systems for decades up until
maybe10 years ago.
The idea here is that each can have its own on cpu its own memory,
its own locally attached disk.
Right?
Think of like mvme and the only way that nodes can communicate
with each other and see other portions of the database is to send messages
over the network.
Like if i'm running on one node on the left,
and need access data on the right, I just can't peek into.
It's disk.
I gotta go send a message to send me that data.
The database is going to be partitioned to destroying subset across these nodes,
sometimes called shards,
where each node will have a right unique portion of the database of tables.
And ideally,
you want to pick a partition key that reduces the amount of data transfer
you have to do.
When you do joins.
We'll talk a little bit this next class,
which is historically a very hard problem to do.
But it does make a big difference.
The challenge is going to be now that since the storage is tied to the compute,
I can't easily add either more capacity at the compute side
of the storage side without bringing in a whole new node.
Now, if I bring a whole new note,
i've got to do re partitioning to move data around,
to balance things out.
Again, we'll discuss the implications this.
And so sorry,
each of these are also kind of quantitative.
This is, when I say, I know this, I one of these.
The other thing, too,
is that because data is considered local like what they locally attached disk,
traditionally, a database system will access the disk using it,
like a posits api or nvme like it'll be a sis calls to go read data,
directly disk.
There's the you can do kernel bypass,
which the stories need to play in kit from intel.
That's a nightmare.
We'll talk about that later on.
But in general,
you're using posits to do reason rights to the local desk.
If I need to send things over the network to communicate with another node,
make the perfect calls into it as well.
The alternative approach for the shipment is called shared disk.
And with this one now,
is we still have every single database data system node that have
their own cpu memory and disk.
But that disk on that each node is gonna be essentially just a cache,
and that the persistent data or the persistent files of the database system
is going to be down on this separate storage layer.
At the top here, we'll have the compute layer.
This is where we're gonna execute queries.
They can communicate with each other over network of the network,
but that their storage is essentially used for ephemeral data,
either a as a right through cash in case of snowflake
or a holding area staging area for intermediate data.
But the node is essentially stateless,
meaning if it crashes,
the compute layer of the node is stateless, mean it crashes.
We don't lose the database because that's all stored
down here in the stories there.
And the the storage essentially looks as one giant disk.
It's not entirely true in an object store,
but because you don't access it through a positive cpi you use a use
like aa user space,
api that the cloud vendor or the whatever the object store.
If you're un they would provide.
In the reason why this matters instead of using the positive cpi
because if it's a positive cpi the database system is not aware of
of maybe the the different physical occasions of the data.
I you would have different file pass and so forth like that.
But like the data system,
it would just see,
here's some file system ii can read and write to and maybe not understand
or could not push down,
like the selects in the filtering stuff that we talked about before
if you're using a of using posits,
because there's no way to do, hey, read this,
but also filter some stuff for me down and storage there.
This to recap everything,
the two choices we share nothing.
And the pros and cons of this that it potentially achieves better performance,
because the each data system node,
if it's accessing only data is local to it,
it'll perform better because there's less data movement
potentially between the nodes,
right?
And I said with modern mvmvme drives with pcicpcie five or six.
The lower the lays one is those things pretty fat pipes,
but you can let that you can get.
But and modern networks are pretty good that it is too.
So traditionally it was always gonna be faster to read from local disc
than over the network,
but it's not always the case these days.
But the big challenge is going to be harder to scale out capacity,
actually, in both directions up and down.
But ii can't add new notes without shuffling data around to sort
of re balance things we participate.
I can't take notes away without doing the same thing with coalescing.
Now with a sheer disc system,
a a in a modern setting in the cloud,
the great big advantages that would be able to scale out the compute
there and stores are independently.
Meaning if i'm by myself being cpu bound on my nodes,
then I can add new compute nodes because they're stateless.
I don't have to do,
I don't have to move a lot of data around to rebound things.
Again,
the snowflake paper talks about how to use consistent hashing to change
the assignment of what files are processed from
persistent storage layer to the new nodes.
But that's you're warming it up.
And this telling here we got here.
Here's the data you start processing.
It's not you have to always copy things from one note to the other,
which other has,
if you want to do that safely and not have any false positive plus negatives,
requires you to use transactions.
It's a little bit more complicated.
The other nice advantage, too.
And this matters a lot in for sort of database systems that want to claim
that their service.
I can shut down the compute layer that That portions that i'm not needing,
the knows i'm not needing if i'm not exiting any queries and the data
doesn't go away again,
in a shared nothing system,
because the computer is tied to the storage.
If I shut down a computer,
know what that means that that portion of the database that's stored
in that node is no longer accessible.
Whereas if I shut down compute nodes in a shared disk system,
then the other remaining nodes can go get data from the share disk.
No problem.
In a service abiding,
this can make a big difference because you can shut down idle things.
Then last one is the disadvantage we talked about.
If I had to go retreat persistent data that isn't cached
locally in the computer node,
I I had to pull it from the share, just layer the storage layer.
And maybe I can do some early filtering that we talked
about from amazon or azure.
But that that's not always the case,
because it depends on what the filter is actually want to do.
Like you can't do another new complex rejects or execute audf on s three,
right?
They're not going to do that.
Our focus going forward.
The rest semester we're gonna focus on shared systems.
Now, for some of the algorithms we'll talk about,
it doesn't actually matter like the joint algorithms.
They don't know,
don't care whether it's reading from shared disc or share nothing system.
Because at that point of when you're actually computing the join,
you've already scanned the table, right?
And fed it into a scan operator.
So it doesn't matter where it came from.
But just in the background minds,
going to be mindful that we shouldn't think about,
if i'm scanning this table or scanning data,
what does it mean to be coming from s three or an object store?
As I said before, traditionally,
the in a shared architecture,
it was assumed that the storage layer was was initial.
The stories with me some dedicated
on prem appliance or storage device or knobs that expose like a
posits api that you could read and write to.
In the more high end systems like rural exeter data,
they do use a storage appliance.
These racks are looking for this.
You have to compute in storage layer,
but the the daily system is aware that it's talking
to aaa special storage storage appliance.
It goes over fiber channel,
and it's not making positive calls to read data.
It's extending proprietary commands.
They actually can do some predicate push down in these systems.
But the systems, the environment we're gonna focus on, as I said,
is the object stores.
Because this is how everyone's building these modern o lab systems
around the cloud.
And then I said is that they're infinitely scalable.
Put that in quotes, obviously,
but like as long as your credit card has enough money on it,
your account has money on it.
You can keep putting as much data as you want in amazon s three
and a local outlet stored for you with pretty high guarantees
and durability,
insane for azure in gc ps cloud storage.
So you no longer have to worry about provisioning storage space,
but he would have to do a a in a own premise system.
You just keep throwing more and more data in your stores layer.
And you don't have to scale you scale compute layer separately either.
You just keep putting more data in and things are great.
These object stores what do they actually look like?
They're gonna expose you a pretty simple api we talk about the amazon select,
but in general,
they're going to have three commands put, getting delete.
So what happens is you have these,
you have your data that you're ingesting,
put your database.
You're going to break them up into to these large immutable blocks of data,
these files,
and you can do it put in to store it in the object store.
Then you'll have some catalogue that'll keep track of for some file.
Id is found at this location in the object store.
We'll talk more about what these files look like next class.
But in general,
they're going to be some binary format of a column storm and 1 kilometer format.
And it's gonna use a pax layout where within each block,
the attributes of the table will be broken up in a columnar fashion,
but all the attributes for a single logical triple will be found in that block.
This is different than how,
like maybe the vertical store files, store data,
where you have a separate file for each column at a table.
With packs,
you basically have all the data within a single attribute in the single file.
There'll be a header.
Sometimes the footer,
like in part k will contain metadata about the offsets when the file
for where columns start,
what kind of compression schemes are using for the different columns that
can change per profile?
Sometimes there's pre computed indexes to do filtering or zone maps.
Again, these are things will cover later in the semester,
but he would store all that information within the file itself.
Now, when you want to start accessing this data in the object store,
you would make a request on the other store just to retrieve the header
of the of the file block.
And then that'll get all that meta data about where the columns are located
and what kind of professional teams are being used.
And then you can then do selective gets just to get the byte ranges
of the data you actually need.
So you don't need to bring in the full page or the full block
from the object store and then parse it.
You can just bring a little bit in figure out where you need to go to get
the rest of it.
Have retrieved this the minimum amount.
Again, that's different than what we talked about doing.
Disk io in the interclass where we'd say every pages eight kilobytes
or four kilobytes,
you go fetch the whole thing.
Even though you only need a portion of it,
you can be a bit more intelligent here, because the blocks are larger,
and you obviously don't want to achieve the whole block.
I think in snowflake, the block size is,
I think the lowest is like 50 megs, and maybe goes up to the corner,
max or something like that.
I see these aren't small blocks.
These are pretty big.
So you don't need to fetch the whole thing if you don't need it.
So one interesting system I like to bring up is yellow brick.
So this is actually a slide from a talk they gave with us
during the pandemic a few years ago,
but it shows this sort of how they're using the object store with s three.
Again, this architecture looks a lot like what i've already showed you.
You have these worker nodes,
and they have this locally attached mdmmessd
so it's interesting about yellow brick is
that they talked about how they tried using amazons,
s three library,
the access library to communicate with us three.
And they found it was super slow.
So they wrote their own library.
They were to get a three x performance using retrieving the same data
from s three using their custom library instead of using amazons.
I'm bringing this up just to say that you don't necessarily,
you don't have to use whatever that the cabinet provides you.
For the client side library.
You can write your own thing and potentially get much better performance.
I forget what the secret they used here.
They might be doing.
You may be doing kernel bypass to get through the optic store,
and you can use on the client side.
You can't do it in the server side because amazon controls the server.
But I another cool thing they were doing is that they would communicate
between the different nodes using udp with the intel
dpdk which is the data plane development kit.
It's a way to do kernel bypass on talking to the nick, which is,
she's not easy to use it.
Again.
We'll talk about this later.
All this.
Intel current life passed off is like super tricky and super painful.
We'll cover that throughout the semester.
I there's a bunch of other stuff that we're not gonna talk about today,
but we'll start covering these things over the next throughout the semester.
There's different file formats.
Again, I mentioned the tax layout,
but we'll talk about different approaches.
Again, all this is gonna be very,
highly depressed because it's kilometer storage.
To talk about next class.
How do you actually decide how to do horizontal partitioning on your tables
and split them up based on values?
So you can minimize the data transfer between nodes for inmate results.
Then there's a whole process of how you wanna do ingest new data.
Like a big part of databases are absolutely you want to put data in it.
There are there's fast path instead of running a certain
as fast as new bulk loading and get hit
into the system quickly as possible.
Obviously, want to get update attention, delete it.
How do you handle that?
Even though the files are immutable?
And then we're not gonna talk about too much about this,
but this will come up.
We talk about data lakes, especially with the photon and database later on.
But the a in a monaco system,
you also want to support the ability for people to have existing files
just sitting in s three.
They can see in a party format without having to first bulk load them
to your data system.
You want to be able to operate directly in the files as exist.
How you discover that these files exist?
Then what have you scheduling?
Productivity will spend a little time talking about.
It means that as the query is running,
how do we maybe make changes on the fly to better utilize resources,
maybe under provision or over provision,
the task or the workers and we can scale that and make changes as we go along.
Again.
There's a lot of things we're not covering here.
That are important.
We'll get to later this semester.
Ii talked to this at the beginning when I make an observation here,
that in the snowflake paper, you guys read,
even or even though it's about snowflake,
they talk about snowflake does certain things,
but they make some important observations about,
again, what a monolith system looks like.
That's why I had you guys read it.
But the thing to.out,
a system like snowflake, like drama, like big query, like yellow brick,
like data bricks.
These are monolithic systems,
meaning that they're building all the components that that you need
for the data system.
These are monolithic systems,
meaning they're building all the components you need to build.
It is entirely in house with their engineers.
Most of the non academic systems that we'll talk about the semester
are going to have pretty much the same architecture,
right?
You have query engine, you have some storage layer,
you have an orchestra to move data around xe task, scheduler, some sort,
right?
They're all pretty much implementing the same thing.
And that means basically that we have people where they have companies
in a lot of money,
writing the same database and software over and over again.
Right?
They're writing the same thing to do the same thing.
And obviously, that's a it's a huge labor effort to do this.
And it may not be in the best interest for the database community,
broadly speaking, to do this, right?
If everybody's implementing the same sequel parser,
what is that actually that moving us forward?
Right?
We may be better to be better spent doing other more innovative things.
And so there's this interesting development in the last5 years or so,
where you're starting to see various projects
of in the own source committee or organizations to
build to break out portions of a modern overlap system
into standalone components that are open source
that other people could build on.
Other people could take advantage of,
and other people could could reuse either I for their own new old lab systems.
Right?
Again, the idea here is that everyone said, everyone,
everybody the same thing,
this all redundant parts of the system.
Let's everyone work together on one thing and have that be really,
really good and everyone gets to reap the rewards.
They're sort of like linux, right?
Linux is,
but it'd be kind of stupid now or insane outside of research and academia
to try to build a new operating system from scratch and to compete
with linux,
where the sort of potential wisdom where the mindset is,
everyone spoke about linux is what we're using.
Let's make that really, really good.
It's not exactly the same because the os is a major undertaking
where these other parts i'm talking about are much smaller.
But the idea is the same thing.
Right?
Instead of having two people build competing parts that do the same thing,
let's work together.
You see this in sort of 4 sort of categories.
And it's you can sort of see how this is tied to the different layers.
I talked about the beginning, right?
There's people getting system catalogues, query optimizer,
which is the hardest part of the system is file for us to act.
So I want to quickly go through these different components and just sort
of talk about the major efforts,
the major projects just can be aware of that as we talked
about the semester for these different engines and different systems.
A lot of them aren't going to use these things,
but they'll be potentially open source alternatives for them.
This idea of breaking the system up into reusable components
or modular components is not new.
There's this paper by a famous researcher at msr surgery,
where he back.
And I think it's like 19 year, 2000,
we talked about what they call risk dial data systems.
Now,
this argument here is built for how to make these different sort
of sub components modular,
reusable,
to make it easier to automate the tuning of them,
make of autonomous navy system.
But the idea of, again,
breaking the system into these separate layers that can be implemented
through some standard pi is basically the person that they were talking
about this paper long ago.
The first thing is the system catalogs.
Again, we're talking about this next class,
but system catalog basically is the registry where the data system keeps
track of,
what the schema looks like.
Potatoes they have,
what calms they have if there's persistent files where they located
in the object store on the disk.
And so the way basically works that if you're calling your talent assessment,
insert the data for you,
like an insert query or copy command,
then the data some will maintain its catalogs because it's trading
the files as it goes along.
If there's a discovery process, as they said,
where there's a bunch of existing three files and the catalogue
needs to have an epi needs a way to be told these files that you beware
of them.
There's now several projects where people build these sort
of cloud catalogs that essentially,
again,
just keep track of what data exists,
what cables and columns are in these files.
Sometimes there's some basic statistics about what's in them,
but as I said before,
oftentimes the statistics are stored in the file themselves.
Probably the most famous one or why the used one is the h catalog.
And this came out of the hive project.
It's a wrapper of the hive,
meta store.
And I know you can use this for spark.
I think there's some other systems that take advantage of it.
Again,
think of it's like a key value store that keeps track
of again the database schema.
Google has its data catalogue,
amazon got its blue cattle data club.
They're all doing basically the same thing,
but h catalog is actually the only one.
The next is the query optimizers.
So we'll spend a several classes talking about query optimization,
but think of these are just generic frame works where you can define
the heuristic or the cost based search rules to do career acquisition,
how to take a some of them actually keep the parts the sql query for you,
but then it convert it into a a logical plan through transformation rules
and then run a cost based search to generate a physical plan.
The hardest part of building data system
because there's all these corner cases and sequel is
all these optimization rules they can apply.
Deal with correlated sub queries like it gets very messy, very quick.
And the ideas that rather than everybody building
their own first crappy heuristic optimize,
which everyone does.
In theory,
you could have a cost based search that was pretty powerful out of the box.
The two nodal implications are apache,
calcite and green lump orca.
Calcite is came out of lucy db lucy db a was ai think,
commercial system,
late 2000s that failed.
But for whatever reason,
calcite was pulled out and was reused,
getting as a standalone query optimizer, which is pretty cool.
And then the green thumb guys built this thing called orca.
It was designed to be the query optimizer for both green plum,
which is a lab system, as we talked about last class,
that vm ware now also vm ware owns.
But they also built for this other thing called hawk,
which is like their version of sequel on top of head do.
And so they try to build a single optimized framework that could be used
in both systems.
I hawke is still around.
It's not that people actually use it,
but green plum uses it as well.
The main thing is to think about this green plum is less known than calcite.
It's written in c plus.
Calcite is written in java,
and that's more use that there's more systems using calcite.
I don't know whether which one is more powerful or not like.
They both look roughly equivalent.
Then there's also these source file formats.
And actually a this is a pretty novel idea that is definitely
made possible by the amount modern cloud systems.
So historically database systems always use their own proprietary data format,
right?
Seek a light, postgres, my sequel, whatever you name it.
Then when they write files to desk,
that's in their proprietary binary format,
like you can't take up progress data files and read them in my single oracle.
Duck tv can read single light files, but it's designed to do that,
but you get my point,
the only way to really transfer data or be able to take data
from one day system and reuse it or do computations on another day system
is if you dump it out as acsb or jason file,
right?
Starting in the last decade,
there was this moment to say, okay,
let's actually build these binary file formats.
So we don't have to dump.
It is like text based formats like jason.
Then we can build libraries for these different database systems that
can access this stuff very efficiently.
These libraries potentially,
suppose you're an iterator to retreat batches of columns in these files.
You can do some select the scans for like pick which columns you actually want.
And some of them, do they do all the depression stuff for you?
But again, they're just like this.
The lowest level of the query plan is the access methods.
So these are probably the six most wide users are famous ones.
In 2013, there was parquet,
org and carbon data came out.
Parquet is probably the most widely used one.
This is a compressed column on my format from claudia and twitter.
It has more aggressive the compression than work,
whether or not it's fast or not depends on what the data looks like,
depends on how you actually access it.
So I can't say one's better than another, depends on a lot of things.
But at a high level,
they're basically equivalent or came out of facebook high project.
Carbon data came out of hawaii.
And as I said, I think in the inter class,
i'm working with a former student of mine.
They actually tried using carbon data and all the open source libraries
don't compile,
don't work.
So I don't know if anybody else at hawaii that uses the carbon data.
Iceberg is a newer one at a net flicks and we'll see it
over this next class where it's a way to do support updates
and scheme evolutions over parquet files so that you can do,
they have a delta store, you can do updates and then apply them,
do the party files plus read the historical data.
85 is a much older data format from the scientific community.
Come from late 90s.
This is for multidimensional data.
Again,
I don't know of any sort of commercial database system that uses ht five,
htf five.
It's primarily used for, as I said,
for scientific calculations, scientific instruments,
and then apache arrow a is a memory kilometer format that's designed to be
the exchange format for
sort of sharing data between processes and over the network very efficiently.
Again,
think of like it looks something like parquet,
but it's for enemy data.
For our class, this class,
we're mostly going to be focusing on things that look like parquet and orcanero.
And then for project project one,
which we'll discuss next class,
will be building a foreign data effort to parts of it,
looks like a parking file without exactly.
Ok.
The last one that's super interesting is the standalone biopsy,
query execution.
This is kind of what the whole point of this class is.
As I showed in the very beginning,
we spend a lot of time talking how to build the execution engine,
how to do vectors execution,
how to do code compilation,
how to do joints.
That's the it's not the hardest part that he's not always the query optimizer,
but this is certain the part that,
like can have a huge impact on performance.
Obviously, degenerate credit for your plan.
You're screwed anyway,
but like having this during this rate can make a big difference.
So there's now work being done to build standalone query engines that are vectors.
It is all the modern techniques that we talked about before.
Again, input just a dag of physical operators.
They've required something else to do the scheduling and do access,
to get the data,
do illustration and do data around.
But the end of the day,
it's like the kernels are essentially the query operators.
The mixed famous one of this is going to be velox,
which we'll spend time talking about at the end of the semester.
But this is actually very fascinating now,
because vectors query execution is sort of what made snowflake so good,
so unique.
At least it was the starting point of making it so unique.
10 years ago,
right?
That they were building.
One of the first effect rises,
data, use engines.
Now it's so complex.
Everybody has vector x execution for those words.
But can you just go?
This was a big deal,
but now facebook is building velox.
There's data fusion from the arrow and influx tv guys.
Intel is so ethnic.
So now this is super interesting because no,
facebook is gonna spend a lot of time building up this execution engine
that anybody could come along and build a wrap around and make the
next snowflake and not have to worry about writing the execution engine.
Essentially,
this becomes a commodity like a vector execution engine using
the modern techniques of today.
It does not differentiate one system for the next.
It's now gonna be the communication between the different nodes,
sort of the yellow books that we talked before.
And then all the query optimizers.
Yeah, we're good.
All right.
My boys in there.
I got teaching class.
I'm teaching class.
I wrote like,
I is like this other guy.
He's almost done.
He's coming down.
We got from the fbi no,
it's like, okay.
Like, thanks.
Anyway, so this is super fascinating.
We spent a lot of time with us.
All right.
So,
right.
So the this was supposed to be the high level approach,
a high level overview of what the query optimizers look like.
Again, as I said,
the way you on a single node itself,
you would build these systems is not where each worker knows
not different how you build a single data system.
It's gonna be that data movement stuff that we talked before.
And also, again,
assuming that we're coming from retrieving data from a cloud based
expert shared disk.
So the rest of the special we focus on how to build
these different components that we talked about and make them using
the modern techniques.
Right?
Next class, we'll talk about storage models.
We'll talk about how to represent data within the column themselves,
the bytes.
I do table positioning and then in system catalogs as well.
So hopefully I got to deal with these guys,
forgot what's going on with him.
Hopefully they'll be done soon.
And then then i'll film the next class and post that on youtube as well.
Later on the next class,
we'll talk about project one.
Hi, guys have a good night.
See, you.
That's my favorite.
All that.
What is it?
It's the st cricket idesi make a mess unless I can do it
like ago ice cube with the
g to the e to the t it comes.
Do I play the game?
Where's no roof?
Tommy saw the custody of a group of sun treat group with the buzzing cap
on the aisle.
For sure, we going to go with a blow to the aisle come on.
What is it?
That's me rolling with that?
What's up pork and sap it to see and then ask what a party.
By the 12 pack case on the 46 pack,
48 gets the real price.
I drink fruit, but you are drinking Bob 12 hours.
They say bill makes you fat,
but saying eyes are straight,
so it really don't matter.