Hey, yo, yo, pack the chrome stuff by like mrs.
Jones, liverpool, mathematics.
We have the devil spoken stone,
upward heads to bed,
make shots and records, sorry,
for being out in the last week,
how to go to seattle for yourself.
Then my co curve inner low,
so like I was trying to do much extra stuff.
I wasn't around her when she was sick, which is edible my time.
So I apologize for not posting this lecture while I was
gone and also not like updating the schedule.
As I put some piazza.
This is basically the class we should have had last wednesday,
but we'll start today.
And then everything's been shifted up by one.
And then we dropped the materialized view lecture.
A lot to cover today.
Let's jump into this.
Today's lecture is about sort of the talking about the lowest point
of the database system,
meaning like how we're actually going to represent data in the database,
on disk and in memory.
What are the actual bits of the bytes for representing tuples
and their attributes and their values and so forth?
And what the data is going to look like is going to have
a a very important impact or
influence on how we're going to design the rest of the database system.
In particular, we're going to talk about row storage versus column storage,
because that was the paper you guys just assigned reading,
just whether it's a row store or a columns or where the data is laid
out in rows or a commentator format that determines
so many different aspects of the system and the different design choices
we can make.
Like how we're going to process two poles,
how we're going to move data from one relational operator to the next,
how we're going to materialize the intermediate results as we go
from one operator to the.
Next what algorithms are going to use like some joins we faster on,
because we're a column store, because our hash has to be much smaller,
whether or not we're going to support ingestion updates that one will cover
a little bit today,
but we won't go too much into this.
Actually, not until we talk about data breaks at the end of the semester.
For current control, how to support transactions,
we're actually going to ignore all this as well.
But like think about,
if I need to update data to pull that, split up into columns,
now,
I gotta go acquire latches or locks for a bunch
of different physical locations in on desk or in memory to do that
update.
Again, we're going to know that for now.
And then query optimization is influenced by all of this.
The query optimizer should know has to know what the database is actually doing
to determine what's the best query plan to use.
Again, just in the back of your mind, as we go along,
even though today we're only talking about the lowest levels of the storage
layer.
You will see that as we go out throughout the entire semester,
that a lot of these things will,
the decisions we'll make now will determine how we make
other decisions later on.
Another challenge, also, too,
is there will be times when they will start talk about certain techniques
in the storage models,
where it will.
The solution to a hard problem is what we will cover either next class
or next week.
In particular, the fixed length data versus the variable length data.
The solution is dictionary compression,
which we will cover next week.
So the paper talks about these things,
but we won't go into too much detail about it just yet,
but know that these things are also coming up later on.
Today, we're going to focus mostly on the storage model.
Again, row store versus column store versus the hybrid store.
Then we'll talk about how we represent in visual types.
And then we'll spend a lot of time talking about how to handle partitioning
at a high level.
First thing, storage models.
A storage model is gonna define how the the database systems
going to physically organize tuples on disk and in memory.
Now, I say the database system is going to organize.
This is as if it's responsible for actually laying down the bits in a file.
But as we said before, in the modern olap system,
in this data like model,
it could be just much of existing s three buckets that already have csv
or parquet files in it.
And the data system just knows how to read it for our purposes to assume
that the database system is the one generating this data.
But as we know, it isn't always actually the case.
So there's be three choices.
N-ary stores, the row store,
decomposition storage model, that's the column store.
And then the last one is the hybrid store, the pax model.
Again, the paper you guys read came out,
I think in 2006,
it is the defendant paper, my opinion, even though it's old,
it still is like the good,
the best first paper or the best paper that started describes
exactly the pros and cons of a row store versus column store.
Whatever it's old.
Again, you were one in middle school.
Elementary school like, yeah, so it's old, right?
It should be dame is already at yale by then.
He wasn't at mit anymore.
But like there is a textbook that they wrote about how to build column store systems.
I obviously didn't want to assign that to you guys,
because it's 100 pages.
But this is a I think,
a good summary of the pros and cons.
The thing i'll point out is they mentioned the pax player and they cite it.
They don't actually go into detail,
but this is what par k is, is what ork is.
This is what all the modern systems are using.
Right?
But we'll cover these.
And then that'll lead into why we want to do the last one.
And then most systems today,
when they say they're a column store,
chances are this.
They're packs.
The n-ary storage model, the row store, row store model,
is the database system.
I'm going to store most of the attributes for a tuple continues
with each other in a single page.
The reason I say almost is that in most systems that will support
like very large variable length fields,
like a text field of our binary.
For anything above a certain size,
they then all float it into auxiliary storage pages.
Postgres, they call this toast.
I think, in like oracle or my sequel to come overflow pages.
Right?
You don't inline them.
So that's what i'm saying almost.
But we can ignore blobs for now.
So the row storage is going to be ideal for lot workloads,
where most of the transactions are only going to touch
single entities or entries in the database.
And then we very insert or update heavy workloads.
And so by single entities, this means like,
think there's a table of user accounts and you log in,
you're using some application, you log in,
and you only touch your user account,
maybe millions,
but each individual transaction is only accessing a small number at a time.
And so with this storage model,
the iterator processing model or the volcano processing model,
which will cover in a few weeks.
This is the ideal processing model for these workloads and for the storage model.
Because most of the queries accessing a single at a time,
a single tuple at a time,
the operator can just go grab that one tube and then feed it up
to the query plan to the next operator in the query plan.
Most of the data systems that are going to be row stores
are typically going to store database page sizes in some constant multiple
of what the harbor provides you,
the largest atomic page size you can get largest page size that harbor
provides that you can do atomic writes,
four kilobytes.
And so most database systems,
when they have their database pages,
it'll be like 4 or 8 or 16 kilobytes, right?
They won't go really big.
As we see, we will see in in a column store system.
Right?
The reason because if you're doing updates,
you don't want to try to do a one megabyte update across a bunch
of four kli pages,
and then crash halfway through.
And you got to go back and fix things up.
So they try to keep things in smaller period size.
It essentially looks like this.
Say I have a assembled database that has 6 rows and 3 columns,
a in a disk oriented system,
all of the pages,
all the data that's going to be,
but fixed length and variable length,
we want to pack them together into a single page or does not work.
We have our database page here.
Again, some say it's four kilobytes.
There's always going to be a header.
Then you have the slot array.
Again, this is just a slot of page design.
These slots are going to point to locations in the page where you can find
the given row.
Now, if another part of the system like an index wants a reference,
a to pull in a row ended architecture,
you need to use the page number and then the offset within a slot array.
In that way,
you can move things around in the page without worrying
about having to update your index.
It's an additional layer of indirection.
Say, I want to assert this first to pull up here.
I'm going to put it at the end of the page and have the slaughter
a now point to the header for this.
The way it works is the slot array will grow from the beginning to the end.
And then all the data will grow from the end to the beginning.
Right now, I want to start the next table, and I just, again,
append it to the end here and then update my slot array.
All right.
I can do this for all the other ones,
and you end up with something like this.
So one thing to point out here is that every single tuple,
we're going to have a little header space for it.
In the page.
This will keep track of which values are null.
Any other additional metadata.
I typically don't put the schema there because that we store
that in a centralized location of the catalog,
because otherwise, it's it's redundant, right?
All the tuple within a single page are for the same table.
So you don't need to store that over and over.
Again, this header up here may contain like maybe check some for the page,
the version of the data system that generated and so forth.
But it's a lot for each single tuple.
There's a lot of that you're maintaining its own header.
Now, let's say I come along with an overlap query like this, really simple.
I want to scan the entire table and find all compute the sum on column a
and the average on column c for all two poles that are column a is
greater than 1,000.
The way you would process this query without even disgusting what
the processing model is,
the way you would execute this query,
which is on the single page,
you'd have to jump into it.
First,
go look at the header for every single entry as you scan along the slot array,
find the header, check to see whether the value for column a could be null,
and then do the comparison.
So I go fetch this page from disk.
Now it's in memory, my buffer pool, and i'm doing this.
I'm jumping around from 12,
go to the next following the slot array to go start processing it.
And then now if I want to start computing the aggregate,
then i've got to go back and scan through again and maybe jump
through all the c values here.
On modern cpu.
This is actually terrible.
Right?
Modern cpu are super scalar architectures are designed for optimized for
for things that are very sequential and deterministic.
Meaning i'm going to scan through the same thing over and over again,
and not worry about arbitrary jumps into memory.
I I get better cache locality as well.
We'll see how to design scan operators and predicates to take advantage
of super scalar architectures by removing indirection.
But in general, here, i'm jumping to different locations.
And that's going to suck.
Right?
For this example, it's a simple.
It's a 1 page who cares?
Again, think always in extremes,
if I have 1 billion pages or 1 trillion pages,
this is not very efficient, right?
Because i'm bringing in data also, too,
that I I don't need b five.
Right?
So I don't need column b but I had to bring that data into memory.
And i've got to skip over it where every tuple has a header.
And I I got to deal with that.
The row storage model, again,
it's going to be great for fast updates, inserts, and deletes.
It's going to be really good for queries that need the entire triple.
So I have a question.
So it's great for queries that need the entire tuple,
because It's all located together in a single page.
I go fetch the 1 page and it has everything I need.
Again, ignoring overflows.
We're not going to discuss this semester,
but it's great for,
you can use it for index orient storage.
Like if you store it,
if you take a  b+ tree like mysql in innodb where the leaf nodes are
actually the two tuple themselves,
you get the clustering effect so that you can do binary search
on the leaf nodes and get faster performance.
And you try to find certain keys.
But this class we care about olap systems.
So it can be terrible for scaling large portions of the table when he
only did a subset of the attributes,
because the data is going to be sort of jumping.
The location of the economy will be accessing.
It's spread out across the single page.
And you're bringing in other attributes that you don't need for the query.
So it's going to pollute your buffer pool memory.
As we said before, it's bad for memory, locality, and access pattern,
because again,
i'm doing these jumping instead of doing sequential reads.
And then we'll discuss this next week,
but this would be terrible for compression,
because now within a single page,
I have a bunch of different data that comes from different attributes that
are all going to have their own different value domains.
I'm not going to exploit repetition or redundant information and compress things.
If you ever try to take like a zip file,
or like an mp4 file,
if you try to run zip, when it compress it,
it's going to be terrible because it's binary data that doesn't have any patterns.
Essentially, if you intermix all the attributes within a single page,
then you essentially giving this having the same issue.
The solution to this,
which we all sort of know about,
let's cover more detail,
is do a column store approach or a decomposition storage model.
Right?
Decomposition storage model is how you would describe it in sort
of the academic literature.
Nobody really uses the word dsm people to say column store.
But again,
when they say columns are the usually impacts not the sort
of the formal definition of what a dsm is.
See that here with a dsm is that the database system is going to store
all the values or a single attribute in a table.
Continuously one after another.
Just think of like a giant array.
Here's all the values of column a there's another giant array for all the columns,
all the values of column b this is going to be ideal for olap workloads,
where we do read only queries.
And we only access a subset of the attributes,
because now we just go get the array,
the rays of the data that we need,
or the columns of the data that we need and ignore everything else.
We're going to want to use a batch vector processing model,
where as I process the queries or I execute the operators,
instead of patching up one tuple at a time,
i'm going to pass a vector of tuples at a time that it all correspond
to a single column or a subset of columns.
Now, i'm not paying that penalty called get next on my operators.
I'm just moving large chunks of data from 1 operator to the next.
So in this world,
the files are the term file versus page versus chunk versus pro group
can be all slightly nebulous.
But again, assume these are like par k files sitting on s three,
but file sizes are going to be much larger than you would typically have
in a row store.
Think of like hundreds of megabytes where the page size is,
like tens of megabytes or 22 megabytes or some larger size.
And then over, even though that we're going to have,
maybe store these columns as separate files,
we still want to organize the two tuple in such a way that we can keep track
of where they're located by offsets in these files.
Also, what it means in the next slide,
say, here's our data, same tip we have before 3 columns, 6 rows.
What we're going to do is take all the values from column a and just store
those continuously a in a single file.
Again, there's only six attributes,
but I can think of it extremes, right?
You would have this giant file,
mybe, a billion entries.
There's gonna be some header at the top that it says,
here's the data that here's about metadata about what's in this file.
Again, check sums or what version of the system created it.
Now you're going to store also a null bit map separately in the header,
instead of storing it in the header per tuple.
And now you used to have this giant bit map at the top and says,
here's for all by10,000 people's in this file.
Here's the bits that are set to true or set to one.
If the value for that attribute,
I think the given tuple is null,
right?
And then you do the same thing for the next column and the same thing
for the next column as well.
In these examples here,
and i'll say this multiple times,
i'm showing that the header like the metadata about within the file is
in the header,
a in an immutable file like parquilla orc.
This is actually in the bottom and the footer.
Because the idea is that it's a you construct the file once you don't know
what's going to be in it until you actually process it and create the file,
then you go to pen the metadata in the footer.
Where is it in a row store or a system where you're supporting incremental updates?
That you typically put this in the header.
So for illustrated purposes, i'm showing the header,
but real assessments will put this in the folder or parking,
or put them in the footer.
Right?
Again, the basic idea here is that for every single attribute,
we have a separate file,
and we dedicated metadata in the top to tell you what's in it.
One key difference between a row store and a column store is the way
we're going to identify tuples.
Remember, I said in a row store,
it's going to be the page id and then the slot number offset typically have,
I I can't think of any other system,
every except in memory systems.
But this is how every sort of disk based row system is going to work.
There may be additional things like there might be a file id and an object number,
like oracle and mice and segal server have a bit
more complicated addressing schemes.
But in general,
it comes down to a page number and an offset in the slot array.
In a column store,
we're going to instead use is the offset within the column itself.
So I say I have 1,000 tuples
Ii know how to jump to the header,
the location of where our column starts.
I know the size of every single attribute.
They all have to be fixed length.
I'll explain why in a second.
This is why.
But all the attributes will be,
the values will be fixed length.
I know if I want the 500 tuples,
I take the size of the attribute times 500.
And then I jumped into that giant array of the column.
And that's how I find the data that i'm looking for.
I could do that for any column.
So I know I if I jump into column a if the 500 tuple,
I can do the same thing in column b and column c this is
why all the attributes have to be fixed length.
But we know that every attribute is fixed length, right?
I have a text field or varchar,
binary field, and so forth.
We're going to need a way to convert them back into fixed length.
This is where dictionary compression will come in.
What if there's a null value?
The question is where if there's a null value in the middle,
this question is, what if there's a null value in the middle?
You would still mean you would still reserve the space for that null
to pull or the null attribute.
And then you mark it in the null bit map when you do a look up now,
like you would say,
if i'm jumping to your exact tuple,
or if I wonder what the value is,
I could look in the null bit map tells me whether it's null or not.
And if it's not, then I go look at it.
Right?
You can just think of this as vertical partitioning.
The reason why it's called the decomposition storage model,
because the idea is that you take a regular row store table,
and you do vertical partitioning such that each column is stored
in its own 1 column table.
That's the metaphor people use for this.
So I said that most, as far as I know,
every system that I could think of is going to use this fixed length
offset to identify individual tuple.
We need this for stitching things back together later on,
as i'm scanning along,
trying to find a match or something,
maybe I evaluate the first predicate and the second predicate on the next column,
I need to know what are the triples that match in the first column,
and then go look up their corresponding offsets in the second column.
Again, we'll cover this.
We'll cover this in a few weeks,
but that's the basic idea why we're using this fixed length all sets.
We always know how to jump to within any column to go,
get all the values we need for any one logical to pull.
As I said, most systems are going to do fixed length all sets.
In the research literature,
there is a discussion about how could spark variable length values.
So instead of actually storing,
keeping all these things be fixed,
like you actually embed the,
like a tuple id in the value itself.
I think i've got some kind of 32 bit integer.
So that way,
if i'm at this offset here,
and i'm looking at 2.2,
you have some index or some way to jump into these other columns to get
to people to this.
Is a special case.
I don't remember the system actually does this.
Ii this shows up in that literature in some places, but nobody,
as far as I know,
nobody actually implements it this way,
because there's obviously a huge storage ahead of maintaining this
plus the index and then jump into the other columns,
get the value need.
Instead, everyone just does these fixed length all sets.
As I i've already said this,
but like we need to convert any variable length data into fixed length.
An obvious trick to do would be just to pad out any strings with spaces
at the end to make it fit.
Like if it's a char 16,
but most of the time i'm storing 8 characters,
pat out the remaining eight,
that way, everything's fixed length.
But this is wasteful.
And it's expensive because now you're copying data.
That's actually you're looking in data,
examining data that's wasteful.
And you now use string detection.
You've got to look for the offsets or look for the padding.
Instead, everyone's going to do the dictionary compression stuff.
And the idea is that were to take anything that's variable length
and convert it down into a fixed length integer.
Usually 32 bits.
Again, we'll discuss how to do this,
but basically think of a there's 50 states in the united states.
Instead of storing the string for all 50 states over and over again,
it's a variable length.
I just convert the state into a number, the email.
I store the number.
That's a very high explanation,
but that's basically dictionary.
Compression is going to do for us.
All right.
So I said that con source is not new.
The original idea was actually proposed way back in the 1970s,
from the swedish military in a system called cantor.
It's in the research literature.
I don't think it's gone went beyond what were the prototypes that they
were doing.
And it wasn't a database system.
It was a it's actually a like a file system,
storage approach, like an object store, almost.
But the paper clearly defines like we sort things of columns and things
are faster.
In the 1980s is when they actually proposed on the academic side that
formalized the decomposition storage model.
It was out there.
People really didn't pay attention too much.
In the 1990s,
sybase came out with this thing called sybaseIQ which is in memory,
sort of query accelerator,
will be the fractured mirror approach.
We'll see in a second.
Basically, they would take the regular side base row store,
and they would suck data out and then covered it into a column store.
Your query showed up,
they would try to figure out how much can I run on the column store.
The 2000s of when this really took off,
the packs paper came out,
I think in 2001,
there was ac store project at mit it was a bunch of startups in this space.
Vertica, vector wise and mode adb vector wise,
we're going to see a lot later on the semester because they're the ones
that sort of invented the vector rise execution model processing model.
And they did a lot of the early work and using cindy to accelerate operators.
Again,
the guy that created vector wise then became this was the co founder of snowflake.
I think a lot of ideas were developed in vector wise that made it into snowflake.
And then by 2010s or 2020s, pretty much,
everyone is a column store.
Now,
like this is clearly the better way to go.
I can't think of any analytical.
There are some systems that are claiming to do real time analytics.
And they are sort of doing a row store approach,
but they'll build column oriented indexes.
what's that?
Yeah, we should remember that anyway.
This is the old duct, db log.
We would update that.
Anything else?
Add a date on this?
I paul is still there,
but anyway,
no query engine.
But I it knows how to operate on parking a data.
So like,
is it actually a comes from database in that it can generate kilometer files?
I think it does ingestion.
It's on the critical path,
but it's certainly designed around assuming that it's operating
on columnar data.
It would be fair to say it is a column data system.
What are the pros and cons of this?
Again,
the the obvious advantage is that we're basically getting projection pushed
down for free,
because we only bring in the data we need for the query,
only the attributes of the columns that we need.
We're going to get faster query processing because we'll be able to take
advantage of the increased locality and better cache data usage
of the data we're accessing,
because of ripping through columns and only accessing the columns
that we actually need and not having to jump around over stuff we don't.
Then again,
we'll get better compression because all the values within a column,
for the most part,
could be very similar to each other.
I just think of like.
And they can think time stamps, right?
Some event stream, the time stamps,
there are 1 second all for each other.
So that means that there would be a lot of redundant data from one tick
to the next and we can exploit that and get better compression.
The downside that's going to be slow for point queries,
things have to go grab a single tuple.
Anytime you can do insert updates and delete,
assume your system supports that,
not all of them do.
Now we've got to take tuple that come in from the application
as a row store and then split it up and store it in separate columns.
Or now we've got to take the columns and the separated data and put
it back together,
stitch it back together,
return that to the client.
And any time with the reorganize things,
then that's always expensive.
Like we won't go in this too much,
but there are some systems.
They would sort all the data in your columns.
Now,
anytime I insert something that maybe lands in the middle of my sort order,
i've got to move things around to make space work that gets expensive.
Right?
So this sounds great.
So the dsm seems like what we want to use,
except that we know,
as i've already said, in the last slide, like,
is a penalty we're paying for having the extreme case of everything
separated from everything else like restoring
the columns and completely separate files.
Because most queries in olap setting aren't going to be going
only accessing a single column.
Right?
Very rarely you're going to say like select id from table foo
where id equals something right?
Like or id greater than this.
It's very rare that the olap query,
but only look at a single column in isolation.
So that means at some point, as we execute the query,
we're going to have to go back,
get the other attributes for all the tuple that are matching our predicates
as we're going from one operator to the next and then stitch
the tube back together.
The paper you guys read,
they discussed this as you want to do this as late as possible.
This is the late materialization technique.
But you still need someone, you still need to do this.
The idea is that we want to get the benefits of the columnar storage
for compression execution reasons.
But then we also want to be able to take advantage of having data
that's related to each other,
close to each other.
Maybe not exactly the same page,
but at least nearby,
so that we can not have to do a bunch of more random io to go put
things back together.
We want to column our scheme that gets, again, the separation,
but had things at least be,
again, relatively close to each other.
So this is what pax is.
Pakistan sort partition attributes across.
This came out in 2002.
This was invented here at cmu by natasha alamoky,
who used to be the data professor at cmu and then she left to go
to epfl in switzerland.
I'm here because she left not entirely all of it.
What's the reason why the last time this class was taught before?
I revived at 7:21 was like 2006 because of her.
She's great.
So, again, as I said,
this is gonna be this.
We still call this a column hour storage format.
This is what parquet is.
This is what orc is.
This is what basically carbon data is.
This is what most people say.
When they have a columnar database, it's actually pax.
But this outside academia,
maybe it's less well known.
So the idea here, again,
the goal is that we want to have the faster processing benefits
of column storage,
but they maintain the spatial locality of having data that's close to each other.
They're related to each other.
And that's part of the same tuple physically close to each other.
So the idea looks like this now that we're not going to break things
up into separate files,
separate pages,
assume that there's a single file.
First we're going to do, we're going to horizontally partition the rows.
Could be on some key.
Some attribute could just be the insertion order within they arrived
in the system.
It doesn't matter for now.
And so we're going to take all of the data that's been maybe the first23 rows.
I'm going to put them together where all the attributes for the first comma
are contiguous,
all the attributes of the second column are contiguous.
And then the last one as well.
I'm going to call this a row group.
Every rogue group's going to have its own header that says things
about like what compression scheme they're using,
where to find the offsets for these different columns.
Again, don't think about row group as a single page.
Right?
In this world, these files are usually quite large.
So the row group could be like 100M.
Then a in a row group,
you have the data for a single column that could be broken
up into multiple pages.
Or I think Parquet goes some chunks,
right?
And you do the same thing for now for the next row group.
All right?
Then again, as I said before,
in mutable file formats like parquet,
the header would actually be in the footer,
but this is going to contain information about it.
Here's the location of the row groups.
Here's just maybe check some for the file,
any other global metadata.
But the metadata about what's actually in the tuples themselves.
They activates themselves.
That'll be tied to the row group.
Yes.
By playing it up into the row group,
we still maintain the column and factors.
But how do we maintain the row advantage?
If the row group is split across multiple pages?
This question is,
I how do I still get the benefit of locality?
If the if the columns may be contiguous?
But within a single tuple,
the columns themselves are are still separated,
because it's still close enough.
Right?
It's not like completely two separate files,
permit the optimal size for a group.
Her question is, has someone determined the optimal size of a row group?
It's funny to mention this.
My former student huang chen,
who I co advise with dave anderson.
He's now xinhua.
We are actually working on the survey now looking at parquet and Orc
and understanding the pros and cons.
We have found that in the modern systems with modern network hardware,
like the speeds, the defaults are actually terrible,
but the defaults are actually too small,
because again, these fall formats were designed 2011, 2012, thirteen.
The networks have gotten way faster.
Right?
Cpu have gotten that much faster,
but the network and disk have gotten way faster.
So we won't talk about this class like,
you can also then take this pax file.
It'll run snappy or z standard compression on it.
It turns out, again, your disc is really fast.
You don't want to do that because the cpu cost of decompressing,
it is not worth the benefit because you can suck it in way faster than you
used to.
So this is not maybe the best way to do this.
Well, however, this is the best way to do this.
There's a lot of studies on this term that you get the benefit of the cash locality.
And as all the things that i'm saying before,
but exactly what these parameters are,
how long these strides should be, chunk sizes,
all that depends a lot of things.
Parquet is also more heavy weight with compression.
I think they have the compression scheme is way more complicated than orc.
Sometimes simplicity, this is better.
I think i've said everything here, right?
Again,
every row group has some metadata.
We're not going to go discuss exactly.
Here's how parquet does works.
But if you go,
there's a bunch of talks where they basically describe the same thing
i'm describing here.
This is from data bricks of how,
what part k looks like.
Right here we go the rogue group,
and they says default 128.
And the page size is one megabyte.
Is that the best?
It depends.
But for faster however now,
right?
We're not going to discuss the buffer pool side of this in class or this semester,
because we're just going to use all the same stuff we talked
about in the angel class at the end of the day,
like there's stuff on disk.
You've got to go bring it into memory.
You don't want to use m map,
said multiple times, right?
We want to manage this stuff ourselves.
Underneath the cover is like, what is if we mallock something?
What is actually is that I it is anonymous m map,
but we're not letting the os aside what gets evicted.
So all the things about like lruk or arc or preventing from issues
of sequential flooding.
All that still applies here.
The thing I do want to talk about is because we are in an olap setting,
and we are trying to bring in larger page sizes than we would in a row store.
What does that actually look like underneath the covers at the harbor level?
Right?
What's the default size in hardware?
And sorry, what's the default memory page size in linux 4 kilobytes?
Why?
Because that's what intel decided for x 86 and 1985.
Right?
There's been attempts to try to have larger page sizes.
I think arm tried to do this with 64 kilobyte page sizes,
but then it broke a bunch of stuff that was assuming four kilobytes.
So they had to roll back in linux.
The reason why this is bad because if we're now reading really large files,
really large chunks of data,
we're going to rip through that as quickly as possible.
Then having the operating system,
the hardware keep track of these little four kilobyte,
sort of pages, even though the block of data or reading might be,
100 megabytes is going to be expensive,
because in the tlb the translation look left side buffer inside on the hardware.
It only has so many entries.
So to bring, I think,
the fastest, smallest cache,
at the first level,
I think you have seventy two seventy two entries for your tlb so it's really hard to bring all that in and update your tlb if you're going at four kilobyte page size,
next slide and give me a sec this.
He said, can't you always configure this machine to use huge pages?
Yes, this is where we're going.
But he ruined it, right?
So huge pages.
So instead of allocating 4KB pages,
you can turn on huge pages in linux.
And you can get larger page sizes.
I think it starts with 2MB and you go up to 1GB.
And so when this first came out,
this was tao does this huge improvement?
Because as I said, we have larger memory machines.
We're reading large data sets.
This is mean way more efficient.
So the way it works is that you would allocate memory just like you
normally would with transparent,
huge pages.
And then underneath the covers linux to try to identify these pages
can be combined together into larger page sizes.
Then you have fewer entries in your tlb right?
The the way it works is that the pages that be contiguous sort of identify,
i've mallocked,
these continuous pages that are physically close to each other.
I can just combine them together and then use
a single reference or tlb entry for them.
The the os is going to try to do this in the background.
So it wants to keep things compact, right?
Once reduce fragmentation.
So it's going to look for maybe pages that could maybe split up to larger
to smaller page sizes and to combine them together and reorganize.
Right?
The downside of this is that when this is happening,
this is now a kernel thread that's going to block the database system
when it tries to access one of these pages,
if it's starting to move things around.
Because, again, there's virtual memory that's mapping.
There's mapping from virtual memory to physical memory.
It can prevent you from accessing virtual memory.
If it's changing where that physical memory is actually backed from,
what that virtual memory is backed by, like, what region of memory.
When transparent, huge pages first came out,
all the data systems basically would tell you turn this off.
This is a terrible idea.
It's all in the documentation and all these links here to go look at it.
Everybody tells you to turn this off,
right?
Because the performance everhead of random stalls,
because the os starts come back in your memory.
Terrible.
The only system that i'm aware of,
at least I can find,
and more recent search is vertical.
They tell you you can turn this on,
but only for some new version of redhat or centOS
where somehow it's been fixed.
So historically,
database systems, even though we're especially in olap systems,
even though we're reading larger page sizes,
are larger blocks of data,
they don't want you to use the huge page mechanisms in the database system,
because the because of all these penalties for the os is doing stuff
that we don't want to do,
or the system is not aware of.
So more recently, though,
there is research that seems to suggest that having a version of maloc that
is aware of these huge pages and trying to allocate for
them can actually make a huge difference.
Google has a paper from 20,
21 where they turn on huge pages in tc malloc as their version of malloc,
and across their entire data center for all the workloads,
they saw a 7% improvement.
And then for specific explicitly for spanner,
there's a transaction system, not an of system.
They solve almost a 6.5% improvement.
So it seems like this would be a big win.
The current research literature suggests that it is not, at least sorry,
it's not research.
It's the basically all the blog articles,
a much a bunch of bench reggae i've done for existing database systems,
seems to suggest huge pages aren't the way to go,
but the google paper suggests that it's worth reconsidering.
There's a blog article written actually last week by a friend of mine,
where he basically says this is something we need to reconsider
in column databases.
Because clearly this is what we should be using, right?
This is a no brainer.
But as far no database system can do this negatively and read the benefits
of it.
I think you can turn this on in jvm think you turn this on and go.
But again,
ii haven't seen anything that suggests like all the olap as we talked
about for you get the benefit.
Yes.
Don't enable large pages, but then now enable it.
His question is what has changed in the last couple of years that that
suggests that you could turn this on before you could.
Because the background compaction stuff is now less aggressive,
and it stalls less is going to interview this.
How the question is, how difficult is it to implement this?
I you call m advise and use huge pages,
and it is that enough?
No, but that's how easy it is to do.
But like I said,
the data needs to be aware that maybe it's using huge pages
and maybe configured its memory allocations
to be aware that i'm allocating 2 megabytes to block that can be
contiguous to something like that.
Instead of like 4KB 8 chunks over and over again.
Yes.
I don't know if you can answer this question.
It's the current question.
What's the point of implementing huge pages like just from an os perspective?
The question is,
what is the point of implementing huge pages from an os perspective?
I the benefit is obvious, right?
It's tlb.tlb is like super small,
like it's like l one, l 2, 03, actually, it is l 128.
What's that?
It's a brain dead question.
Ignored me.
No, it's not a great question.
It's like the question is like, why do we want this?
Because again, in an olap system,
we're reading terabytes of data potentially for a single query,
for the general onwatch masses,
for like, wait for random programs or javascript programs.
No, that's an honest question.
No,
just like regularly feel like what is get regularly what
like so like just abbey your database user again,
likes,
ii don't know if you have to allocate memory and
the memory you need to allocate is going to be contiguous.
Then you want this.
If i'm doing a bunch of small little object allocations and random locations,
it doesn't help you.
You don't want this.
But again, what are we doing databases?
We're reading a a large chunk of memory.
Do you read large contiguous data?
It's not a super question.
I it's good to figure.
Again, this is like it.
It's a good thing.
This is why you have to think about.
You want to think about what the data set looks like,
what the query looks like, what the workload looks like.
And you can design a system for the olap workload patterns.
You can take advantage of these things.
This doesn't make sense in for otv workloads, where you're going again,
doing random updates on random locations,
small amounts of data.
It's a question about what it has changed.
It used it again.
If it has to figure out where to go, do compaction in the old days,
it would take seconds.
And the new one in the newer versions,
actually think like version four in the kernel,
like if it can't find anything right away, then it backs off.
Whereas before it would like lock, everything stall,
we actually want to represent data.
This is basically the same thing we talk about in the injure class.
So there's nothing really dramatically different here.
For for a bunch of prototypes,
integers begins and floats and reels.
We'll just use what's in the I triple east, 74 standard.
And this is a standard that defines what the how
hardware or cpu manufacturers will represent these
low level data types,
like integers.
You can think of like I allocate a variable in c plus for an integer.
It's going to be 32 bits.
The hardware defines this.
The standard defines how the hardware should actually represent it.
And they'll be instructions.
And registers should actually store this data accordingly for time stamps,
depending or not you, whether you want the time zone.
But typically, it's going to be a 32 bit or 64 bit integer.
That would be some number of unit management since the unix epoch is
the most simplest way to do this for very linked fields,
like bar charts or binary text and blobs.
The value is less than 64 bits, so you can just inline it.
Otherwise, again,
you'll have a reference to some other off overflow storage,
whether it's in disk or in memory to where to go find it.
Again,
most systems are going to use dictionary compression for watch rs to make
things fixed length,
or the address itself to the off load storage.
Overflow storage will be fixing.
The one interesting I do want to spend time on is talking about decimals.
There's basically two approaches, right?
You can have variable precision or fixed point precision or and the idea is
that like,
do we want to have let the harvard handle the decimals for us?
Or do you want the database system manager for us?
The tradeoff is going to be if we let the hardware manage it as defined
by the 74 standard for either 32 bit or 664 for bit floating number,
floating point number,
is going to be faster because the hallmark can support it natively.
There will be instruction that take two floats and add them together.
Did noah used to be that case that came out on the 90s
with floated point units in the cp us?
But now every modern cpu hasn't.
But the problem is is going to be that they don't guarantee exact values.
So I wanted to write this in rust for chi, but it didn't have time,
but it's the same amount of code.
Right here, we have a simple c program.
We take 2 floating point numbers.
We have 0.1 and 0.2.
We're going to add them together and print it out.
And what do you get?
What do you expect?
0.1+0.2=0.3.
But is this actually what's going on?
No.
If I make it print out all the values, right?
I don't round it off.
And you see you get something like this.
Right?
Why is this happening?
Again, because I triple the 754 standard,
doesn't define how to store exact values for floating point numbers.
If you actually look at what within the bits are being stored,
you get something like this.
Depends exactly right.
Again, that's the answer for everything in databases.
Is this going to be fast?
It depends.
Is this the right way to do this?
It depends, right?
If it's the temperature in my office,
then you have a sensor every 1 minute.
Then who cares?
If it's like a scientific instrument,
like trying to land something on mars,
probably don't want to have these rounding errors,
because at large scale, it's going to be problematic.
The way to handle this, oops, sorry.
The way to handle this is what's called fixed point decision numbers.
The idea here is that this is a data type that's implemented
in the data system itself,
not in the hardware,
where we can manage the exact precision and scale of an integer or sorry of a
decimal without any rounding errors.
The segal standard you would define this for 30 bits would be numeric or decimal.
Sometimes some systems that are just alias for each other.
Again,
this data type is implemented differently per database system.
It's not something that, again,
there's the single standard specifies how to do it.
The single standard specifies the behavior.
You should have these data types.
But how you actually implement it is different from one system from the next.
In case of actually, oracle,
I don't think you can't actually get the the variable decision,
the float point numbers.
But if you say I want to float or real,
you actually get these.
Right?
You get the fixed point numbers.
Because the idea is that the just avoid any problems with rounding errors,
force everyone to use the fixed.1.
They made it fast enough that you can't really tell.
There is a way I think you can specify.
I want exactly the variable length one or the variable precision one.
The basic idea is that we're going to store some kind of watch are
or a bite stream of the value.
And then we'd have some extra meta data to say where the decimal point is,
what the scale is and so forth.
If you want to support arbitrary precision,
meaning like the decimal point can appear in different locations from1
value to the next within a single column.
Then there's some extra meta data you gotta store within the tube of cell
to keep track of that.
If you don't need to put support that where every single value has
at the death point,
exact same location,
you can go way faster.
So we had a project on this a few years ago on a library called lid fixing pointing,
was when we were building a noise page,
we built our decimal type from inspired by the germans,
which we'll cover later on.
They're people we don't cover that,
but like in the umbrella in hyper,
the head german there told us how to do this.
Thomas norman told us how to do this, and he's not the head german,
but he's the best german.
He told us how to do this,
but they can't open source of the code and had a student start to implement
it.
So we have an implementation of this.
Does I need someone to help work with me to this library up?
I we could try it out in postgres.
So this could be aa potential project.
The math works.
It's super hard.
It's a lot of bit shifting to make it work,
but the performance is quite good.
Let's quickly look at what postgres does.
This is their numeric type.
This is the actual code of postgres.
As you see,
we're not going to go detail all these things.
Here's a bunch of metadata.
They have to store four integers per value plus this numeric digits array,
which is just a alias up to unsigned char.
You take whatever the size of this is, which now variable blank.
Then with 16 bytes here,
just to store one value,
this is pretty heavyweight.
Then if you go look at the extra source code here, this is how they do.
This is adding two numerics together.
You've got to check whether one's null,
got to check whether one's positive or negative.
Like this giant switch shaping here.
There's a lot of work you have to do to make sure that you end
up with exact values.
It's not a poster thing.
Here's my sequel.
Basically the same thing, right?
A bunch of metadata.
Right?
You have this decimal digit things and aliens up to this,
which is just an array of thirty two thirty two32 bit integers.
And then they have their own and function again.
So think of this.
To add two merits together,
i've got to invoke all this code versus a single instruction to take
a floating point number and add the two together.
Again, you pay the penalty to have exact precision.
And again, if it's your bank account or scientific instruments,
you would care.
Now let's talk about nulls.
The way basically everyone's going to do it is this one here.
The second one,
you have a header somewhere that there's a bit map and a bit of set to one.
If the attribute at that offset in the column is null,
it isn't the only way to do it.
Another approach to do is if you really care about storage space,
is it used actually a special value in the domain of an attribute
or the type to represent null that you typically see this
in memory systems,
because you don't want to maybe pay the penalty or the memory overhead
of of maintaining this bit map.
We just say,
in 32, the minimum value in 32 defined by the c that's going to be my null.
You make sure that nobody can insert that value,
just make the total possible value.
You could store one once smaller by one.
Votb does this.
There's a couple of other memory systems that do this.
The dumbest idea is choice three,
where similar to the two pid you would embed in the we talk about column stores.
You actually embed a flag for every single value that could be
null to determine whether it is null.
Right?
We even though the flag only needs to be a single bit,
can't store it as a single bit,
because you have to worry about a word alignment or cache alignment.
Right?
I can't just have.
You can, but it's a bad idea.
You don't want to find a data type.
That's 33 bits,
because the harvard isn't set up for that.
When you go try to read 32 bits,
you're actually going to read 64 bits even larger,
because it's a cache line, but we can ignore that.
This is actually as a spoiler.
You think it's so terrible who would ever actually do this.
Mem segal used to.
This is the old documentation.
They've since fixed this.
But when you go look at their integer types,
they would tell you the size of each type.
And they would have the size of it can't be null.
Sorry, the size of it could be null.
The size of it.
If it can't be null for a bullion,
which is just1 or zero.
If it's not null, then it's 1 byte.
But if it could be null,
then they have to store that as2 bytes.
Big int, you go from 8 bytes up to 12 bytes.
And they're doing this because they worry about word alignment of the data
that they're accessing.
That goes back to why,
in addition to why we want to have fixed length values so that we can jump
to offsets more easily is also going to ensure that all our data is
nicely memory aligned,
that we don't try to access a two pole that is or a value that
may be spread across two cache lines.
Because now that has two cache reads instead of one.
Don't do this, but it does exist.
So I debate whether to show you this, like, hey, here's a stupid idea.
Don't do this.
But now about it.
So like,
is that?
Is that a good idea?
We've covered calm stores,
we've covered the pack stuff.
We've covered what the actual bits are going to look like for inner values.
Let's talk a little bit about what how to handle updates.
If you want to do that.
Data is considered hot when it first enters a database system.
This is, in general, not just for a lab system,
but think about your in your own life.
Like when you go to,
I don't know,
twitter or tick tock, whatever the hottest be real, whatever,
only fans, whatever like you go,
look at the latest things.
You don't go back 8 months, 12 months,
24 months and look at those things.
So when data first enters the database,
it's more likely to be accessed.
It's also more likely to be red and also potentially updated.
Right?
And then over time, as it,
as it grows colder, it's less likely to be accessed.
You may only start using for read only queries.
We may want to organize our system in such a way that new data is stored
in a and a in a way that can
be very efficient for quick access for being for.
Well, to be kind of queries.
Then over time we want to migrate it to aaa coral storage system.
This is what sort of the hybrid storage model is.
The basic idea is that we want to have two execution engines,
essentially two database systems that are linked together.
They maybe store things in a row store for updates, for hot data,
and then a column store for colder data.
Over time as things get cold as the data gets cold.
Right?
Either through the expiration process or by observing the workload patterns
on it,
we then migrate it to the column store.
And we can do this in a batch in a bached way.
This is why we can then combine a bunch of data together, put it,
store it in a single file, like a park,
a file or work file,
and then do all the compression stuff.
We want to do all the together rather than trying to do things incrementally.
The two approaches you'll see in your life are fractured mirrors,
and delta store fractured mirrors.
I think i've already mentioned,
but the delta store approach would be what?
Any system that's supporting data breaks has the lake house term
or the thing called delta lake.
This is essentially what they're doing.
The idea is they would have aa separate storage for new updates,
and then over time and then migrate percolates into the column store.
So again,
we need to go through these high levels just so you're aware of what they are.
So fractured mirrors come from comes from an idea from2002.
And the idea is that we're basically going to store a second copy
of the database in a calm store that we automatically updated,
as I said.
So you have your rose store.
That's the primary copy of the database.
Then you have this mirror copy in the dsm and if this thing dies,
this thing crashes goes away.
Who cares?
Because this is considered the source of truth,
the database of record for our database.
We can't lose this.
If we lose this, we'll just rebuild it from this.
All your transactions come along.
They're always going to operate directly on the row store data,
because again,
that'll be optimized for fast updates.
Then we'll propagate things to the column store.
And we'll assume any analytical query gets applied here.
If someone then updates something that then are copied over here,
need a way to keep track of that,
so that any analytical query knows that it has to go fetch the newer data
from the side.
Right?
The delta store is probably the more common approach these days.
I so I would say this is used in in oracles has a memory combinator accelerator.
Sequel servers hard to keep track of.
They have a bunch of versions of sequel server.
I think they have an olf index or apollo engine that uses this ibm blue
is or db two blue.
Is there hamas to accelerate?
This approach is more common in systems,
older legacy systems that already have a huge infrastructure and ecosystem
around the roaster.
And rather than making a whole separate column store system,
they graph this thing on.
So to get the advantage of the existing tooling and then people still get
the benefit of a column store.
It's an engineering slash sort of business decision to go with this approach.
But the delta store the idea is that again just like before we have the we
have our front end row store,
all the updates are going to go in here.
Over time as things get colder,
they will migrate it to the historical data set and the column store.
A tubal can only exist.
The source of truth of the most recent version of a tubal can only exist
in one of these two.
So I I as I propagate it into the column store,
I essentially remove it from the row store,
because why waste the space if I already have a copy over there.
Now, again, transactions come along,
you update,
sorry, the row store.
Then any analytical query comes along.
You have to go figure out is the data you want in either one of these
and then merge the results together.
Again, if I update the tube that i've already migrated,
I need a way to keep track of that and validate it here and make
sure that I know that i'm reading the laser version over there.
It's like the underlying assumption here that the analytical queries are
with all the state of theta.
Or this question.
It is an underlying assumption here that the analytical queries are ok
with old scaled data.
No,
most systems will make a trade off between freshness and timeliness
of the data and performance.
Like I if I care about having the most latest data, it might look weird.
Then I got to go looking here.
Same thing with the other approach.
But then I paid that penalty to go,
parse it out of the row store.
If I don't care,
then I maybe I just run over the only on the stable data here.
The napa system from google,
they gave a talk with us last year,
and there's a paper which we're not going to cover this semester,
but they make the trade off of performance plus timeiness
or freshness plus cost,
because for internal reasons at google.
But it's the same idea.
Again, iii I get better performance,
but if i'm going to pay for it and potentially also get the,
but it's hard to trade it off against having the latest data.
Because not having to go read this is much
better data is on.
Question is,
does this mean the application have to keep track of where is data?
Is what side of this?
The idea is that the data system,
they consider all the database system,
whether or not it's two separate products or whatever.
Think of this as the navy system.
It's responsible for keeping track of what is where.
And for also keeping track of like, when should I move things.
Now, the administrator could define that if the data is order than 5 days,
then move it over,
or has been touched in a week, then move it over.
There's some systems support those kind of rules to move things.
But the data system is responsible for facilitating the movement of things
you already fostered.
His question is this faster than fractured mirrors?
You got less space application.
This one, you're basically storing 2 copies of the entire database.
Now you can compress the hell out of this.
But this is basically think of this approach.
It's like an index like this is an auxiliary copy of the database that I
have to maintain and make sure it is in sync with this thing.
But it's another copy, but this is 12 will only exist in either locations.
Now.
There may be a period where I update something here.
If the system allows it,
I still have the old version here.
And only later once I do compaction or whatever,
then it gets burned out.
But the matter space at the store,
it takes more space because you're maintaining 2 copies than this one.
Have like one row store and one column store.
The question,
is there any reason why these both of these methods have 1 row store
and 1 column store?
As opposed to multiple tears or using both like one?
I guess a could you have a single system that supports like both of us run
a calm store?
No, it's more like this is like delta store, right?
You like store like historical data like call store and then you store
like the delta store data in like a rose store,
but why can't like the delta store data also be stored in the column store?
The question is why can't you store like,
so we're not going to cover this.
No.
So the question is,
why couldn't you have basically asking,
why could you have a column store?
Fast transactions?
Right?
The only system, single store kind of does that,
but like the delta store is like the pen log.
It's sort of the same thing,
but it's within a a single system.
And so it's transparent to you.
Hyper is the only system I could think of that did.
It did transactions checked into the comma store,
but because it's doing multi versioning,
it's storing delta records.
So if I have a bunch of delta as i'm updating for nvcc ted can use a row store.
One other question, like, in both of these cases,
we're not assuming facts.
And then his question is, in both of these cases,
we're not doing taxes anywhere.
No, let's assume this is packs.
I say dsm but columns for packs,
again, for the purpose is going for this semester.
When I say column store, i'm going to mean packs.
I should put column store here to be more generic.
We have 2 minutes left, although still our time.
Shit, never mind.
Let's keep going databases.
Thank you last semester was n again at 10:00 after.
Thank you.
I want to briefly talk about partitioning.
We're not going to go details of how to actually partition, meaning like,
how do I pick the right columns or attributes to split my data on,
because that's an np complete problem.
We don't spend too much time on that,
but in terms of talking at the lowest level, the physical level,
how are we actually going to do partitioning?
The idea here is, again,
we want to split the database up across multiple resources so that we
can take advantage of parallelism.
Even though I showed, when we talk about packs, there's a single file,
and there's these row groups.
You can do horizontal partition within the row group.
There's nothing that says a single machine has to operate on that file.
And the entirety of the file, you could split things up further.
Most systems don't do that, but like there's nothing.
You could,
the idea is basically the same like you could split things across the file.
And then within the file you split up.
Again,
we couldn't grow that.
So in the no segal world,
they're going to call this sholding.
In the academic world, we would say, partitioning again, the high,
basic high in the end.
And then the most they're both talking about horizontal partitioning.
So when we have partitioned data,
when we start execute the query,
we're going to break the query plan up their fragments and run those in parallel.
And at some point,
we need to coalesce the results of the different fragments.
The query fragments are working on to produce a final answer to the user.
Right?
Someone's writing sends a sql query through,
like through the snowflake browser tool,
or like from the command line.
We need to come back with a single result.
So we have to go, even though things are partitioned,
we've got to put it back together.
The database is going to be able to partition up.
Physically in a shared.
Nothing says we're actually moving data and separating from each other.
Again, not specific to share nothing.
You could do partitioning within different files a in a share of this system.
But we could ignore that for now or logically,
in a shared distant work.
And it's a single shared location or shared files in a shared disk system.
But then we assign different nodes to operate on either separate files
or different offsets within the file.
You saw this in the snowflake paper from last week where talked
about how to use consistent hashing.
They sign a worker node to one to one file that's out in their storage.
And then if they add a new node,
they do consistent hashing, they're reorganized.
Make another node now be responsible for that file.
But how many reshuffle thing?
The idea is the same.
They're doing horizontal partition.
What we want to do here is that we want to take a tables, two balls,
and we're going to split them up into disjoint subsets,
based on some partitioning key or some partitioning column,
based on some objective function that we're trying to optimize for.
Like, we want to prove joins.
We want to prove data locality for doing scans or something
for our purposes here.
It doesn't matter.
Then partitioning scheme is going to say how we're going to divide things up.
So hash partitioning is the most common one.
There's some hash function.
You take the attribute,
you hash it, and then you modify the number of partitions you have,
and you sign it to a node that way.
Range partitioning.
If the values ahead of time,
the range ahead of the ranges ahead of time, you can split up that way.
And then predicate partitioning, we're not going to talk about,
but that would be,
I could define aware clause to say,
determine whether something should be in a partition or not.
So the basic idea looks like this.
So we have a table and we have4 columns and say,
we pick this one as our partitioning key.
So if we're doing hash partitioning,
we just take the value that's for each people hash.
It modify the number of partitions we have.
I'm showing these as databases, but it could be files.
It could be different nodes.
It doesn't matter.
Then the value of this hash hashing function after modeling it,
that determines where the data is going to be located.
Now, if I come along, and the most obvious example would be,
if I have a a query that wants to do a single look up on 112 pole
based on this partitioning key,
I know exactly where to go find it.
Right?
I don't have to do any data movement.
I don't have to do any reshuffling when we talk about joins and other things.
That's obviously not always going to be the case,
because i'm not always going to guarantee to join on the thing I
partitioned on.
Snowflake talks about.
I don't forget what the paper talks about micro partitioning,
but we'll see this later in the semester.
Redshift, does this, too.
They try to do some automatic reorganization in the background
based on how you're joining tables together to maybe try to partition
it so that
the data from two tables are partitioned on the same joint key.
The data is local to each other.
But we'll cover this later with logical partitioning.
It's the snowflake approach where I don't actually move data to a physical node.
I just say what node is responsible for operating on the data
and the shared disk storage.
Again, really simple partitioning.
I'm doing range partitioning.
The top guy here gets one and two,
the bottom node gets three and four.
Best case scenario have a query shows up,
and it says I want to get where id goes one.
I it goes to the share dis system.
And ii know where to route it.
I know that this thing, this note here,
it can produce the result.
Same thing here, get three.
You can move like this.
But if I have a query that wants to maybe do get three and two,
then I can make a decision whether to push the query fragment
up here and then get resolved back or copy the value down.
It depends on the implementation that push the query to the data,
versus sorry,
push the data,
the query versus push the query to the data versus pull the data to the query.
That design station that we talked about last class server in the front row.
And they are in the front is dismissed where is moved.
Because there's 3 and 21 can go to a one and a two.
This question is,
but i'm not showing here.
How does this thing know to go here?
Yes, you would have some kind of middleware system in front of this.
I think snowflake calls it what they had some name.
But like there'll be something up here that you submit the query two,
and then it says it looks in the catalog.
It says, I know where three and two is located.
I can make a decision.
Shouldn't I go here or not?
Right?
So the statement is you could break the query in two parts,
then coalesce the results on that front end node.
Depends on whether that front end node is like a a just a router,
or it actually is a worker in itself and can actually do some kind of computation.
Again, for our purposes here, like it doesn't matter yet,
which is sort of a physical partition again,
because it's a shared nothing system.
It has its own local disk,
and that's where it's charred or partitioned.
The data is stored.
So when a query shows up,
it knows how to route it accordingly.
Again, is the idea of horizontal partitioning.
It not just applies for otv workloads.
We need it for overlap because and the day it's gonna be for the joins
and making sure things are partitioned on the same joint key.
All right?
So to finish up,
as I said, multiple times,
every modern ellipse system today,
that says there are column store.
They're not a comment store, they're out of business.
I can't imagine anyone area that says that a column store is going to be
using packs.
The key idea about packs is that all the data has to be fixed lines.
The key idea in a column store,
especially in impact as well,
is that all the data that needs to be fixed length?
And it's not fixed length.
We need to use some method to convert it into a fixed length value,
so that we can jump to offsets,
just doing simple arithmetic to identify two balls.
The most databases in the real world,
in terms of the number of percentage attributes that they have not the size
of the data,
but the percentage attributes.
Most of the time it's going to be integers or numeric values.
Again, we did a survey that shows this is the case,
but most of the data itself is actually going to be bar charts and strings.
This makes sense, right?
Like you have your zip code.
That's a number that's pretty small.
But then like your name or email address a that's a string that's been much
larger.
This is why we have to use a lot of compression or rely on compression
to get this size.
The data is down and also convert everything to fixed length.
That's super important.
Another thing that we're even going to talk about we'll talk
about next class is that you guys are sort of spoiled in this modern era
of these column store systems,
because they're so fast now that you don't have to have
a database administrator spend a lot of time,
spend any time really working on the actual scheme itself, indeed,
normalizing tables to get it down to like a snowflake schema or star schema.
You just take your bunch of parquet files.
You stick whatever system that can process them at it,
and is going to rip through the column very quickly and produce results.
In the old days, like in the 90s,
you'd have to have our dva to sit down like,
let me try to convert things to fat tables and to produce a number of joins
and get things down to be is these giant,
super wide tables,
so that the system was fast enough to or could handle your complex queries
on that.
So people still do it,
db as can do these things.
But a lot of people don't have db as at their companies.
They didn't have a bunch of files and they shove an oil lab engine at it.
That's a pretty big change in how people in the last 10 years
about how people organize data warehouses,
you still have to do joints.
Right?
Yes.
Like why doesn't denormalization provide any certain advantage?
Or it's just not as big an advantage as it was.
The question is,
if you have normalized tables,
don't aren't you going to have the new joins?
The answer is yes,
but the the performance of these systems gotten so fast that like joins are
the most expensive thing you're doing in the system,
most of the time.
But like they're so fast that like it's not worth the effort,
you'll still be an advantage to it of the normalizing it.
But then there's other like soft calls or not soft calls.
So there's other engineering costs and the time to set it up.
But now also,
do you have this dual elements data that like someone's going to understand
what the hell they actually are versus like if you have the role
of data files in a column or storage,
you stuff that he joins in them.
But like now, it's more easy for people to come along and say,
I know it's in this table.
Now we're out of time,
next class, next Wednesday, we'll be here.
If for real, I'm back in town.
We're going to spend time talking about how to accelerate the lab queries
beyond just doing sequential scans.
So i've been saying multiple times sequential scans are super fast.
There are maybe ways to build auxiliary data structures to improve that performance.
The spoiler is going to be that the the paper you're going to read
about sketches also talk about bit map indexes.
These can give you a big hit big win as far as I know nobody does it.
No major system does.
It the most indexes you'll get will be inverted indexes that do
fast like text search.
And then zone maps will be the other thing that everyone
does that's going to be a huge win.
Again,
it's an auxiliary data structure where it's a summation
of the table tables contents that you can use to do early pruning.
That's the best you're really going to be able to do.
Because the overhead of maintaining an index is probably just not worth it.
We also spend time talking about project one and why you can't do it in a rust.
According to she.
Hi, guys.
See you.
That's my favorite.
All right.
What is it?
It's the SP cricket idesi make a mess unless I can do it
like ago ice cube with the
tea to the eat to the tea comes Duke,
I play the game with no roof.
Home is on the custody, I'm a focus on drink fruit,
put the bus a cap on the ice road,
bush week gonna go with a blow to the eyes come.
Indeed that's me rolling with 5th one stop fucking south central g
and thank us when I party.
By the 12 pack case 746 pack 48 gets the real price.
I drink fruit, but you are drinking about 12 hours.
They say bill makes you fat,
but saying eyes is straight,
so it really don't matter and so on.
And.