Hey, yo, yo pack the chrome stuff by like missus jones,
liverpool mathematics.
We have the devil spoken stone.
Up one heads, the bed make shots.
But today we talk about a lot of accents which is sort of as I said,
the spoiler is going to be that some of these a lot of techniques were described.
The modern columnar databases aren't going to support us.
But we'll mostly see the bit map indexes will be mostly used in row store
in database systems that then would have sort of accelerated commoner
access.
But let's go through a lot of different things.
So where we left off,
last class was we were discussing the pros and cons of the sort
of the columnar storage versus row based storage.
And I talked about how most modern olap systems
are going to be implementing some variant of packs,
because that's me better for doing sequential access potential scans.
On a large amounts of data.
There'll be a bunch of optimization that we can apply to make these run faster.
The keeping remember,
two is also all the attributes in a columnar database must be fixed length.
Because the way we're going to do addressing is through offset arithmetic.
We're scaling one column.
If we know what the 1/100 offset within that column,
we know how to do the simple math to jump to the hunter,
offset at the other columns to go stitch two tuples back together.
The other big thing there is that we're going to not always,
but if we assume that or the data system assumes that the data files are immutable,
meaning to write once, read many,
like I write it once and I never can go back and make inline updates to it,
is going to open up a bunch of different optimization that we'll see today,
where if we had to support incremental updates or delete or insertion,
then some of these things just won't work or to be too expensive to maintain.
This is another big optimization or assumption that the modern services
are making.
So the first thing we sort of motivate what we're talking about today is
when we talk about olap indexes,
we have to sort of get all the things we learned in introduction class.
Spout indexes,
like, in particular, for b+ trees.
Or if you remember,
radix trees are tries these tree based data structures, even hash tables,
because in the old tv world,
which is what their inter class sort of focuses on without
explicitly saying it.
These indexes are designed for doing finding individual tuples
or small number of tuples.
With very selective predicates,
I go get andy's account or go get andy's orders,
right?
And in the oltp world also as well,
we're not going to assume that the files are immutable.
Therefore, these index data structures,
the b plus trees going to have to store some extra room
in their nodes to accommodate updates later on.
In the leaf nodes.
On average, the leaf nodes are actually any node in b plus tree.
In a real world database system.
On average, it's about 70% full.
Right?
So that extra 30% is weighted space,
because they want to be able to amortize the cost of someone inserting
new data and not have to do a split for every single operation.
Right?
In the ola world, we we don't need to support increment updates again,
assuming that our files are read only.
And we typically don't need to find individual tuples,
at least the lower points of the query plant,
the access methods on the tables themselves.
When we do joins,
we have to find individual two tuples or values that match.
But if you're just doing scans,
you're not going to look at andy's record.
Or in these orders,
you're going to look at all the orders from some demographic,
like some people,
like everybody lives in pittsburgh.
The data structure that we would use to make oltp workloads run
really fast are not going to be what we want to use
for for analytical queries.
So the question is, what can we actually do to speed up sequential scans?
You have to do clicker.
Right?
Here's a big list of optimization of things you can do.
Some of these things were to cover the semester,
some of the things we won't.
So the first thing you do is obviously data prefetching, right?
Instead of stalling, every single time i've got to go get new data.
If I know i'm going to sequential scan,
you scan a bunch of files or a bunch of pages that are contagious.
Let me go ahead and why i'm scanning one,
start bringing in the next one off a disk into memory.
Then I can,
as i'm running my query,
instead of having just one thread be responsible for scanning terabyte of data,
I could have multiple threads do this.
Run the task in parallel.
I'll get some advantages also, too.
If I can pre sort or cluster the data ahead of time,
because now I know that if i'm looking for things in a certain range,
that once I get past a a certain set of values,
I know that the thing i'm looking for is less than that,
what the value is looking at right now.
I know I don't need to look at anything else.
Late materialization.
We talked about last class where and we'll talk about more of this later
in the semester,
where if I have a column stored,
instead of having to pass around the entire triple from one upper to the next,
we just pass around the offsets,
or just the columns of that I needed at that point of the operator.
I'm copying moving list data around materialize views, as I said,
we're not going to discuss in this class,
but it's sort of a variation of result.
Caching is really simple.
Like, if I have the exact same query,
like select star from table foo,
where id equals four,
I can take that result and cache it.
And if the exact same query shows up, I can reuse it.
Materialize use are way more sophisticated because it's taking
a more complex query,
be breaking it down into to smaller parts.
And then, as I make change to the database,
I can incrementally update materialize view without having to rerun
the entire query,
ideally.
But it's essentially a a it's a variation of result caching.
The idea is the same.
Data skipping is being able to figure out what data we actually don't
even need to read ahead of time and just avoid having to do scans on that.
Data parallelization is where we can use vector rising instructions,
or like cindy to be able to apply different operations or do
different steps in our sequential scan in
parallel on a multiple pieces of data at the same time.
And then code specialization or query compilation,
just in time compilation,
is to generate machine code that does exactly what our scan is going to do,
or what our query is going to do.
Instead of how to use an interpreted system.
There's a lot of things here.
In this semester, we're going to cover these here.
Right?
What is materialized views?
We've already discussed pre fetching an intro class,
clustering sorting.
It'll come up throughout the semester, but not going to say,
I can teach you how to sort data we just use whenever the fastest one is
this time.
Again, a bunch of these things would have covered throughout the semester,
but today's class we're going to focus on data skipping.
You can think of like, again,
all of these are things you can do to accelerate query execution.
So what we're still kind of focusing on the lower bounds of the system
like the storage layer.
So that's why we're just going to focus on this for now.
At a high level, there's two things you can do to skip data.
You can do a lossy approach or a lossless approach.
A loss approach would be approximate queries.
The way to think about this is say,
i'm doing an analytical query like select count star on the number
of website visitors in most systems that doesn't do they don't do
approximate queries.
You would get an exact answer,
would look at every single web visit and count all the entries.
But in many cases,
in many application domains,
you don't actually need the exact answer.
Right?
Do I really care that I need to know the exact number of visitors
to my website to the exact person like999,000,
whatever,
or can I get something that's close enough?
And that's enough for my application.
This technique again is called approximate queries.
There are systems designed explicitly for doing nothing
about approximate queries on top of it
like a non approximate query database.
It was a project out of university of michigan called verdict db they
with bars on safari.
He spun that off as a startup called kibo that basically sits in front
of snowflake and does approximate queries in front of snowflake,
even though snowflake is not in its basic form,
an approximate query system.
But a bunch of these other systems blink.
Tv is a project kind of,
I was a research project out of berkeley and sort of did the same thing.
But these other systems here are like no flight bit query.
They have approximate query aggregates.
So you can call there's count star if there's the count thing that gives
you the exact answer,
there's also an approximate count.
And it's basically using sampling and a way to give you
some statistically bounded guarantee of the acts of the answer.
With proximal queries, you basically say,
i'm all going to say i'm going to be a fraction of the data that
I regularly have.
The other approach to do a lossless pruning or sorry,
data skipping is to do data pruning,
where we're going to rely on some auxiliary data structure
that's been pre built on our data,
or be maintained by the database system.
That's going to allow it to identify portions of the database,
the portions of the data files for a table that's needed in a scan that it doesn't.
Does it need to read?
Again, ab plus tree is basically this, right?
B plus tree says,
I can, if i'm looking up some value on a predicate, and I have an index,
b bus tree on that predicate,
I can get down to the leaf node.
Find anything i'm looking for without having to scan the entire table.
It's basically the same idea,
but we're going to see a bunch of different ways that we can do in this class.
One of the tradeoffs we have to consider as we go along,
and you'll see this multiple times is the scope of this auxiliary data structure.
Like,
what is the purview?
How much data is it as actually covering in its it's the metadata.
It's generated for this auxiliary data structure
versus how selective the kind of filter it could be.
Like think of this.
Like I if I have a always taken extremes of databases,
systems are always going to think about the scope of the problem.
Like on one extreme,
for the scope of one of these printing data structures would be the entire table.
I have 1 billion rows,
and maybe I keep the min and max value for for in a column,
in 1 billion rows.
That's not going to help me skip any data,
because the min and max is basically the entire domain of the column.
Or I could have an isolated data structure on every single two pole.
And that's useless, too, right?
That's the other extreme.
So we want something in the middle where it's going to be
large enough that it's going to allow us to throw a lot of data away.
But,
sorry, small enough that's going out.
So throw a lot of data away,
but not too large where but I said large enough that we throw a lot of data,
but it's not too small.
We're spending all the time looking in this auxiliary data structure.
Then the other issue is it going to be manual automatic?
For most of the approaches, we'll see where zone maps.
In particular, these are going to be automatic.
The decent just does it.
For the bit map indexes, these are things you have to define.
And you have to know like in some cases you have to define what the ranges are.
This class we're only focusing on this.
We won't discuss approximate queries for the rest of the semester.
This how to say this requires, again,
outside knowledge of the external information about whether the application
is ok with approximate answers,
that the data system can't figure out for you.
Like, it doesn't know when you're ok,
a with aa rounding error in your bank account, you're probably not,
but doesn't know that you have to be told I want to run approximate queries.
So we can order that for now.
The considerations we have to have for anything anytime we're doing
data pruning or using auxiliary data structures.
It's going to be how selective we want or how selective these predators
are going to be.
Like if if there's a column that's a bullying value,
and it's every 1 billion two balls,
this column is true.
We don't want to build an index on that because it's useless,
because not just let's scan a rip through it.
How selective the queries are going to panel,
how effective these are,
julia data structures are going to be.
We also have to consider the case of how skew the data is.
Again,
my extreme example where everything is set to true on 1 billion rows.
If I build ab plus tree on that,
or a bit map index on that,
it's useless because I get to leaf in the b plus tree.
Then there's a giant linked list or giant list of all the other triples.
Right?
There's a trade off here that we have to be considered.
Then again, we won't discuss this too much,
but if the data is already pre sorted,
then that's going to allow us to do some optimization that we wouldn't be
able to get otherwise.
So there's a lot of things we want to cover.
Again.
This is just like a quick,
some mortgage board, everything you could possibly do.
There's other things too.
We're going to do our multi dimensional indexes and full inverted indexes.
Because I want to focus on the o lab stuff.
We're going to go through zone maps again, the most common ones.
And i'll spend a lot of time talking about different bit map representations.
And then that'll lead us into the imprints and the column sketches.
The paper you guys read,
as I said before, many times,
zoom maps are the most common sort of data skipping technique
that most systems use,
where the olap system is used.
The basic idea is that these are just pre computer aggregates
for all the individual values and all the values with individual columns,
a of a table.
The idea is that for certain predicates,
we could check the zone map first and see whether there could be any data
in the blog about the reader,
the chunk of data about the read based on the zone map.
If we know according to zoom map,
there isn't then we skip it entirely.
Right?
So say a sample column, it has52 tuple with this consuming a single table,
the single column,
and has52 balls.
There's no map for this.
We could compute the min, the max, the average, the sum, and the count.
Pretty straightforward.
But now my query comes along.
Select start from table where value is greater than 600.
The first thing I would do is go look in the zone map and say,
I know i'm looking for value is greater than 600,
but the max is 400.
So therefore,
I know there isn't going to be a value in this block of data that
could match my predicate.
So I could just skip it entirely.
Pretty straightforward.
Again,
I showed this diagram last class from the data breaks talk when they talk
about part k and lo and behold,
without calling it in a zone map,
right here, they call page as metadata,
the maintenance of the count that's stored in the header of every chunk.
This is the zone map.
I think oracle invented the term zone map.
Maybe it's copyrighted, I don't know, trademarked.
But when people say the original definition was called small materialized aggregates,
that's the original paper from some this paper here from this german guy.
But everyone pretty much calls him zone maps,
even though oracle has him, calls him that,
right?
Again, pretty straightforward, not hard to compute.
And because I guess in the case of parquet,
these files are immutable.
We don't have to maintain this.
We don't have to change this all the time.
We just store it in the header.
And we're done.
As I said before,
there's a trade off between the scope of the zone map and its efficacy.
I have a zoom map on an individual to pull, that's going to be useless.
I have a zoom map on the entire table.
That's not going to be either,
because if I have actually, it could help,
because if I know that the thing i'm looking for is not in the bounds
of the zone amount of the entire table,
then I avoid reading the entire table.
But if in the likely case that it is in there,
then there's no map is basically useless.
And I spent time processing and reading it.
The other planning to point out two of zoom maps is
that they're only useful when the attributes position and the values
are correlated.
Meaning if if the thing i'm looking for,
if on a certain column is and that columns values are completely random,
then the zoom out going to help,
not going to help me again,
because the the value domain that's encompassed by the blockade i'm looking
at could be quite large.
And therefore,
every time I check the zone map,
it's going to come back as true for my predicate.
But I then I got to go scan it and finally think i'm looking for anyway.
Right?
But if I could pre sort the data on the attributes that are in my predicate,
then my zoom map will start help me throw things away.
So again, zoom maps,
is it at index sort of right,
like it's a filter, not an index,
so a filter would tell you is something here or no.
And have to go look for it.
Index would tell you where it is.
This is a filter, but it's still, again,
this is the most commonly used one.
And it's not just like you,
you have to have additional code in your query execution engine to be
able to consider these zone maps as part of the the process of deciding
what data you
actually want to read.
I have off the record numbers from i'll have probably put this out.
They said like,
I think like 80 to 90% of the queries get take advantage of his own maps.
And again, at their scale that's massive.
Right?
So the win for these is quite obvious.
This is why everyone does it.
But again,
it's although 90% of the queries of they're talking about will take
advantage of the zone maps doesn't mean they're going to throw
away substantial portions of data.
It just means that there's some amount of data they were able to throw it away.
And in their world that matters,
if you have like a very large data,
then what's your overhead for like free computing with zone maps?
This question is, if you have very large data,
what's the overhead of pre computing the zm maps?
What's your idea?
Very large?
Pet a bytes,
like most systems don't magically conjure up peta bytes of data instantaneously.
A it's usually a fire hose of something
downstream in your application stack is generating data that
you're now ingesting in storing,
but it doesn't happen all at once.
The only system I the only application I know where this does happen all
at once was the large hadron collider at at cern.
Because when they did the experiment like that thing,
generally tetabytes instantaneously, right?
And they got to deal with that.
Most systems are not smashing atoms, right?
Most systems are like,
i'm collecting sensor data,
or I have people using my website.
I'm getting things in as a stream.
So in that case, I can batch things up.
Compute these o maps.
Again, it's not expensive.
I got to pack it into the file.
Anyway, somebody reading it because I got to split things up into columns.
It's not expensive to maintain.
So the alternative,
another approach i'm going to look at is we're going to spend most
of this class on is instead of using zoom zone.
So zone maps will help you filter out blocks.
If you still want to find things that are actually matching like you want
an index.
For olap workloads,
bit map indexes are going to be the primary choice.
Again ignoring inverted indexes annoying multi dimensional indexes
because those are sort of different types of queries.
Think of things like select * from table where attribute
greater than something or attribute equal something like those.
The full text indexes are trying to find words in strings are text documents.
We can ignore that for now.
With bit that index is the idea is that for every unique value,
a in a column, in an attribute,
we're going to maintain a separate vector with a bit set to one,
whether a tuple at that offset has that particular value.
Again, because everything's fixed length,
we can just use the offset in the bit map to then map to the offset
in the actual data columns themselves.
I th position in the bit map corresponds to the I th position in the tuple.
And obviously,
we're not going to want to have a giant bit map for the entire table.
We're going to do this as we chunk things up in our pack styles
of row groups as we shared before.
Bit map indexes are an old idea.
They go back to the 1970s.
And then there's this paper from 87 that sort of describes the first way
to put it into a database system.
This is just a sample of some of the systems that support bit map indexes.
Post code has these things called brain.
They're going to be range index by binary range indexes.
And that'll be we'll see in range coding,
a second pelosa is now commercialized as feature based.
This is nothing but aa giant distributed bit map index database.
That's all it is just bit maps.
Then you can pino has range indexes,
a bunch of other systems that I support this.
Here's a really simple example.
We have a table has 2 columns, the id field,
and then whether somebody's lit or not,
yes or no,
say we want to build a bit map index on this column.
We're going to have,
since it's a binary value,
yes or no, we only have 2 bit maps.
And so we'll have one for and one for no.
Again,
there's a one in the bit map corresponding to whether the attribute
within the original data has that particular value.
If i'm looking inside this, if I jump to the 4th all set here,
I can check to see that for the lit status is zero for it's one for no.
I know it's no.
That corresponds to the original value here.
This is like a bit map index in its most basic form, pretty simple.
And they will see some ways we can use sim d to make this actually go faster.
You're not actually just running in a for loop and examining bits one by one.
We'll cover in a few more slides,
then we'll cover later in the semester a lot more.
Today's question is, which then leads to this next slide.
What kind of data is suitable to be used in a bit map index?
Because if it's a the worst case scenario, again, thinking extremes,
if it's a auto increment key or serial key,
where every tuple has had a unique value.
That's the worst case scenario,
because I have a bit map for every single one for every single value,
and most of them are going to be all zeros.
Every entry is going to be zero except for one.
And then my extreme case is like a it's a binary decision, yes or no.
That's the best case scenario.
But most things are not that extreme.
It's somewhere in the middle.
Like on.
Her question.
Is her statement?
Isn't it just an edom value?
But no, is the edom?
You only.
No.
He's correct that like this is like,
i'm just trying to show like there's 2 bit maps in a binary decision.
It's either one or zero.
You only need 1 bit map.
Yeah, right.
So how about?
No?
Maybe you still need 3 bit maps.
Like your maybe lit, right?
Yeah, see.
Like, maybe so like you need 3 bit maps,
but to your.like zero,
just having like storing like 1012 or something.
Really, I don't know how I call it a bit now.
Because if you store it, like,
so,
you're basically saying it's basically it's sort of a column.
Right?
We'll see why you want to do this as we go along, right?
You can have more compact form.
I'm not even getting into like e gnom is
maybe also like it's a simplified example where like you could do
the compression techniques and things like that.
We'll go along and we'll see that because we store things in bits.
We can play games to make things run really fast.
Yeah, i'm going to do in.
India is like you have english.
His statement is this only works for categorical variables of values,
which is the same thing, as she saying in enum.
I will say through our analysis of schemers,
most people don't, there's like enum are super rare,
right?
Even though like it may be like in the application, treat,
it really isn't enough.
They define it as an inter, whatever, right?
Without thinking about it to his comment, also, too,
that like it's a category of variable.
But like it'll work on anything like you like,
I think, like an oracle or you can tell I want a bit map index.
It doesn't come back say, hey, that's a bad idea.
I'm not doing that.
Like if it's the worst case scenario between restrictions.
And I it says like,
we're all saying the same thing.
This is my example here to show why this doesn't always work.
They have a dimension table on customer information.
And then we have this zip code attribute here, right?
My query is select id id email address from the customer dimension table
where the zip code is in this range here.
These three possible values in pittsburgh,
I want to build an index on this column here.
If I build it as a bit map index,
then it's got to be fast because if I want to do a scan now to find
all the matches for this,
I just scanned the 3 bit maps that correspond to15216152171218.
And I take the intersection of those.
Now I know the two poles that match,
right?
And I can do that evaluation of bits very efficiently,
much more faster than actually comparing to integers.
Right?
Because I I can pack together a bunch of bits in a single value,
and then do the bit wise comparison on those.
But this obviously is going to be problematic as you guys keep bringing up,
because the value domain for zip codes in the united states
is actually quite large.
Anything guess how many tip codes there are in?
The us 10,000,
no100,000.
All right.
It's less than 1,000, more than 10,000.
It's 43,000.
So if I have 10 million two poles,
and I build the bit map index on this,
I have to have43,000 different bit maps of length10 million bits.
And that's about 5033 gigs.
Right?
The original data of just like 10 million,
30 bit integers is like what?
40 megs.
We're paying a a lot of space for all these bit maps.
And most of the time they're going to be sparse,
much time is going to be zero.
Right?
This sort of naive scheme was like,
let's just create giant bit maps for the entire length of all the tuples,
or the size of the table and have for every unique possible value that I have.
Right?
This obviously won't work.
So we need to be smart about how we're going to do this.
The two design choices we have to consider is the encoding scheme
how to represent and organize the data within the bit map.
In my simple examples, i'm just saying it's a giant.
You mount a giant array of bits,
but we can be more clever.
Then how do we actually compress the size or reduce the size of bit maps
where we know they're going to be sparse?
We'll cover this second one, the next class,
and then this class will focus on the first one here.
The idea again, we want to get, we don't want to, basically we're trying to,
can we get the benefits that we would get if we had a bit map
to do accelerate scans without paying that huge georgia ahead
of these giant arrays of empty data.
The before encoding schemes,
we can consider what i've already shown you is the equality coding.
You just have a giant bit map with for every unique value that you
could possibly have in your column.
With range of coding,
it's a way to sort of store less bit maps for all the unique values
instead of saying for exactly 15217,
and 15216 for those zip codes.
But if I take a range of zip codes and represent a bit map of those values,
and this is sort of what the column sketch paper you guys read.
It's viewed the basic same idea.
Whereas now that means that I could get false positives where I think I
have a match,
I could possibly have a match within some range.
I think i'm matching more triples than I actually I am matching.
Then i've got to go check back the original values
of the original base data and do the final pruning.
So postcards has this,
again with these grid indexes.
Patchy piano came out of,
it came out of linked in, I forgot,
but a it's an open source system or that system that supports makes
heavy use of range indexes.
Again, the human has to specify these ranges.
As far as I know that no database system can actually automatically figure
these things out for you yet.
Hydro coding is a way to use a tree structure to identify the mpu key ranges,
and then not actually have a store them.
We'll see that in the next slide,
and then bit slicing is a way to actually maintain a bit map
of a single bit location a within a column,
and then do a bunch of tricks to speed things up.
When you violate this bit,
slicing is a really neat idea from the 1990s.
I don't think.
He says, maybe I think pino might use something like this or pelosi,
but we'll see the modern variation of bit weaving from wisconsin how to do
this very efficiently,
which is pretty cool.
Let's go through the last two,
because there's not much to say about range encoding.
Obviously, again, it's just the same idea.
Instead of having a bit not per value, you have one per range.
Hydro coding.
The idea is going to be is that we're going to have a tree structure.
We're going to organize the bit map as a tree structure.
Where at each node,
there's going to be a bit map itself.
And that's going to gonna tell you whether the child represented
by the position at that node is gonna have a one below it in the subtree.
In this case here, every node is going to have 4 bits,
every or in its bit internal bit map.
And then every node,
it's going to have four children.
So I a if I have a one in a position,
then that's going to tell me that the subtree pointed down by this pointer.
There's going to be a one somewhere.
They don't know where,
but somewhere in this case here,
the second position is zero.
So I know that in the second child going down,
this subtree isn't going to be anything.
The way to think about this is along the leaf nodes.
These are the offsets in the bit map,
just as we had before.
In this case here, i'm storing,
say, offsets at the top here,
and I have the bits at the corresponding location.
I'm not actually storing the bunch of zeros.
What you're really storing is just the locations where you have a one.
You see,
if I want to figure out whether I I have aa bit set in position one,
right?
I start at the top.
I say, I know I need to look at this side of the tree.
So therefore, the first bit is one.
I know, and not zero.
I need to go down here.
This bit is set to one.
I know I need to go down here and then low and behold,
I can look at my bit map and see that there's something there.
Right?
What are some problems with this i's over here?
He says you decide the size of the tree before the size of the nodes.
That's not hard, right?
Because it depends on the number of values I have.
There will be one friendship outside to just keep sending,
and then well,
versus like it will be a really deep like the type of opportunity.
Really.
I don't know that his statement is that if the again,
so this is a bit map,
this is the thing that says like with someone lit or not, yes or no.
This is just instead of storing it again as a giant array.
This is the array.
So skew this in terms of what's,
because it's the bit set to one that corresponds to like this position
here corresponds to one tube.
Distribution is unique.
And you don't say anything.
It says the distribution is uniform.
If all the bits are set to one,
then you don't save any space.
Yes, you spend more time.
Yes.
Let's say, a little bit similar to that,
but i'm kind of worried for memory optimization issues in terms of locality.
There you go.
And what else?
It's tied.
I what's reading the memory?
The cpu right?
So this seems like a great idea.
It's one of the things.
Again, this idea that came out of the 1990s.
It seems like a good idea,
but nobody actually implements it because on a modern super scalar cpu this
is a part came out of 2003,
but on a modern cpu this is a bad idea,
because now you have this in direction,
whereas i'm doing this probing,
i've got to go look at this bit map,
and I may go down one path versus another.
And then that might be another cache line miss to go fetch this.
Right?
So like the the cost ever had this storage savings you would get is
not worth the sort of the performance panel you pay for using
a probing data structure like this.
Again, think of like trying to scan large things.
Again, it's not get b plus three where I can scan along the leaf nodes.
I'd have to store some metadata,
either store some metadata about where what position i'm in,
and then maintain pointers across to go from 11 node to the next.
Or I have to do a depth first search,
I got to burst down here and then come back up, right?
And that's how I scan along you all the leaf nodes.
All that back and forth is very costly.
In a superscalar,
cpu where you don't want to have stalls in your obstruction pipeline,
because now you're jumping to another location.
So also,
more recently, zone map says if you have all you're writing,
so we can give one of them before these one.
You're missing production of space, right?
So a statement is,
if it's, again,
it's the enum category of value issue, right?
If everything's one,
then this41 to the one.
So like in this case,
if if at least one value,
a in a node is one,
then I have to maintain the tree structure.
These nodes are really big.
I'm showing 44 bits per node,
because I make it fit in powerpoint.
Like if it's something larger as it should be,
a like a cache line size, 64 bytes,
then the likelihood that something is going to be one is, yes.
Correct.
Yes.
Right.
So he's basically saying, again,
just i've got 1 bit set to true,
and i've got to store the entire node.
And the nodes are going to be kind of large.
Right?
Probably a cache line.
So again, this is seems cool, seems clever.
The savings is real.
Are we go from 8 bytes to 4 bytes?
But again, in a modern cp architecture,
this is going to be bad or better off just applying the data ripping
through it.
Let me show you another variation to bit slicing another way to encode things.
For this one, again,
we're going to have our original table is going to have this id field.
And everyone have a zip code column.
These are actually all the zip codes,
the places i've lived before in my life.
I grew up in maryland in the pittsburgh now, compton,
wisconsin, and so forth.
Right?
What we're going to do now is we're going to flip around how we're
actually going to be storing
the data within the values themselves instead of having this bit map to say,
this bit map corresponds to 15217.
And there's a one in that bit map.
If the people has that,
we're now actually going to store the values themselves in bit maps
at a sort of single rate of single in a bit wide manner.
And then that's going to open up opportunities when we start doing
predicate evaluation,
to do early pruning and identifying things that we don't actually need to read.
So again,
think of this as like you wouldn't want to store the table itself like this.
This would be an auxiliary data structure like an index that we
can then identify what offsets in the column and the original table
are matching.
Therefore, we then will need to go get the full data of the columns,
get the process of the query.
Again,
the way to think about bit slicing is that it's like when we took
a row store and convert it to a column store.
But now we're taking the bits that we're storing for each value
And flipping that to be a column store.
This is an old idea.
I think it comes back to actually forget it for the 90s.
Let's take the first value here, 21, 042, where I was born.
If we just convert that to its binary form,
we end up with this bit string here.
Again, I realize in a for,
I showed that the table schema,
32 bit integer, we're going to show 17 bits, just they make it fit.
So we're going to have17 bits for the actual data itself.
Then we'll have one bit map for to identify whether a value is null or not.
In this case here,
the value is not null, that's set to zero.
Then, again,
for every single bit along and the binary representation of the value,
we're going to store it in a bit map like this.
The bit map is going down not across with any single position in the value
of the attribute.
Here's all the bits for all the tuples.
If you do the same thing for all the others.
Right?
Now, if our query comes along,
find all the customers that are in a zip code less than 15217.
What we can do is we can look at what is for this value here.
What is the first position where in the binary representation of the value?
What is the first position of the one?
I therefore,
we know that anything before that is going to be zero and anything that,
therefore,
is not zero within those first positions.
We can throw it entirely.
Right?
So i'm going to basically walk through each slice and construct
a a little bit and say whether a what two boy
different positions in each row matches.
Right?
So15217 is this value here.
The first three bits are zero,
and then we have the one.
What we need to do is we need to examine,
find all the entries here where the first 3 bits are not zero.
Therefore, we know we can throw them out immediately.
Right?
Again, this is we can go in using vectors instructions.
We can do this evaluation very quickly across these bits.
And then we can sort of keep marching along, going down to the end.
And at some point, we realized there's recently and we're done,
or there's no matches having a stop early.
Right?
So this is a different way to think about how to evaluate tuples.
Then, like, here's for loop,
for every single tubal apply a predicate.
Now we're looking a batch of tuples all at once,
while we're doing this by bit across all of them.
So bit slices can be, again,
are used for efficient aggregate computations,
like a really simple trick.
If you want to do a summation on a column,
you can use the hamming weight,
which is just the or hamming distance.
It's the number of ones,
the number of you count the number of non 0 bits,
which is one number of ones within a string of bits.
You walk along the slice and then count all the number ones in the first slice,
and then multiply by two to the 17, right?
Because that's their position.
In integer form,
then you count all the ones in the next slice, multiply 2 to 16,
and you do this.
All of them go going across 1 by 1.
And you add those together,
you get the summation.
And intel added this pot, count instruction,
which basically gives you the hamming weight.
You can do this with cindy very efficiently again,
instead of having to maintain an integer sum,
and then having a four lip looking at every single tube one by one,
you go across these bit slices.
Do this simple math trick?
You end up with aggregation very quickly.
All right?
So for aggregation,
sure this always works.
The challenge course is going back here.
For simplicity,
I said skip any entry where the first three slices have a one in it.
And I was sort of hand waving how quickly we found that out and how we
actually go from down the line.
It's not that efficient.
If you have to look at all the bit slices,
if you can throw everything out in the first chunk,
the first bit slice is fantastic.
That's super fast.
But for larger values, again,
more than 17 bits,
this can get expensive.
Again, you fall back to it.
Can I just scan the data that would be quicker.
So any questions about bit slicing?
How big a word is?
You still have to have the full word within the cpu register
and can only be within the first few bit.
So would you really say much because the majority of your cost
in the database goes in terms of this diagram,
you still have to bring the whole word in to the memory to the cache.
His statement is,
statement is, how much is this actually going to save us?
Because basically,
at the end of the day,
if you have to go get the disk,
isn't disk always going to be the main bottleneck?
Absolutely.
This is sort of assuming once it's in memory,
can you quickly rip through the the data that is in memory
without having to go
without having to go one tuple by tuple or attribute and attribute,
or no way to think about this, too.
Again, we're using this to do data pruning.
So going back to that parquet diagram,
they have the header has all this information.
So if I just bring that in,
then I can identify,
I don't need to read anything else because I had these bit sliced indexes filters.
Then I end up reading less data in total, and that's great.
Right?
And then you can play the trick of like,
doesn't it mean?
I if I check this index,
and then I do have to find something that I got to stall and go fetch why I
get it.
If you have multithreading,
you could bring one piece in,
have one thread chop through this,
while something else is waiting to bring the next piece in and staging that,
right?
There's always index to look at if you then have to hand something up,
say I do need to read rather this data.
You can block that thread and run something else.
Let's talk about bit weaving bit.
Weaving is a modern incarnation of a bit slicing.
And it's specifically designed for doing fast evaluation on compressed
columnar data using sim d is everyone here taking six, 1814?
Does everyone know what cindy is?
Who doesn't know what cindy is?
Awesome, fantastic.
First time.
Right?
We'll ignore how we're doing order preserving dictionary encoding
until next class.
But basically, what we're doing again,
we're trying to get bit level paralysation where we're trying to scan lots
of data,
a a lot of attributes at a bit by bit level,
and be able to identify quickly whether something's going to match
our predicate or not.
So this idea first came from university of wisconsin,
and it was implemented in a olap.
A better lab engine called quick step.
Think of like duct db before duct db which isn't called quick step,
but it didn't have sql, didn't have a parser, didn't have a query planar.
It was like rockdb, but for analytics,
but without boarding sequel,
they rolled us at it was constant,
became an incubator project for apache,
but then in 2016,
but then it got killed off in 2018.
I forget what happened.
He went up and he did a startup.
So this is invented by jeannox, patel.
Again, he's probably along with the germans,
thomas norman and germany.
Probably one of the best data systems researchers in the world.
He's really cutthroat too.
Like every time I showed this picture,
I always say like he would tell me stories about him growing up in india
where he had to like getting on the bus just go to school every day it was
really but he's a super mild mannered guy.
It was insane when he was telling me anyway.
All right.
So there'd be two ways to do this.
And again,
this was in the sketch paper you guys read.
I think they allude to and talk about bit weaving,
but only the vertical approach.
So we'll talk about both of them,
and you'll see why the vertical one is going to be superior.
The other thing I also forgot to point out, too,
is this paper came out in 2013.
The time, cindy,
at least on x 86,
didn't have scattering gather operations.
They're going to be able to get all the parallelism with vectorization
in some cases without cindy entirely.
But also if they are using cindy,
they don't require scattering gather.
Because again, now we have it,
but back then there are the modern versions that do it,
take advantage of it, but it doesn't require it.
We'll cover, scatter, gather,
and stevie stuff in more detail later in the semester.
Again, we're doing this.
When we talk about the horizontal approach first,
it's gonna be row based, but again, think of it.
It's it's for a single column,
even though we're storing the bits within a value in a row oriented manner.
It's assumed that it's on a single column,
and the column will be stored in a column in our fashion,
the attributes we stored in the column in our fashion.
Again,
it's a clever way to allow us to get better parallelism through vectors asian,
because we're organizing bits.
Right?
So say we have our tuples here.
This is just the binary form or whatever the storing.
Here's the actual the numeric value that's being represented by all of these.
We're going to break it up into segments.
Think of these again, just like roe groups, as we had before.
For each segment, we're going to store.
We would know how many values we need to store.
We're going to represent them in sort of this,
a in a weaved manner where we were stored in the continuous memory
will be have gaps where we
would come back around and get the next batch of tuples.
So let me show you what I mean by this.
So think of this,
as like this is the start of memory and goes here from here to here.
We're going to represent these 3 bit values in 4 bits.
You actually have the actual value.
The first one is 0010 is a one here.
But there's always going to be a delimiter that's in front of it.
That's going to be aa padding bit that's always set to zero.
And we're going to use this to then,
when you start doing the arithmetic to figure out whether something that
matches the predicate,
they're going to use this to store whether the triple matches
or not in the output.
You see what I mean in a second.
And the other thing to point out also, too,
is that the way it works is we go from top to bottom t this is t zero,
t one, t two, t three.
Then we loop back around and then append t four to where t one is the same
with t five and so forth.
Here.
We'll do this when we start,
because we need to get convert out or extract out the matching tubes
into a selection vector to know what all sets match.
If we organize it in this way, it'll pop out nicely.
You'll see what I mean in a second.
Then the same thing for the second segment, we know there's two values.
We only have to store222 poles,
and there's the pen in one after another.
I'm showing this with 3 bit values,
with shortest 4 bits.
We'll say this is a process of word.
It's just 8 bits on x 86.
I process a word.
I think it's 16 bits, because that's what it was.
Back in the 80s, I think arm is 32 bits.
It doesn't matter to, for simplicity, we're using this.
Here.
Here's the little emitter that's always set to zero.
Let's see how we might use these to match a predicate.
Select start from table where value is less than five.
We're just going to deal with just two tuples like t one and t four I that I
showed before going back or t zero,
t four.
We're going to deal with this first one here.
The x is going to be the actual triple organized in the bit,
weaving horizontal format.
Then this y vector here,
that's just going to be the constant that we're comparing five.
Then there'll be this mass to just zero with a bunch of ones.
We're going to use that when we do our when we do our arithmetic to figure
out whether this thing,
whether the value is less than the concept we're looking for.
The way it works is that we have this formula here.
We'll have a different formula per based on what the predicate is.
This is for less than you take the x core of the x and the mask,
add y to it and then end it with a negation of the mask.
Lo and behold,
what you get as the output is a selection vector that tells you
whether the 2 point actually matches.
Now, you see in the padding here,
that's where you put, whether the predicate actually was satisfied or not.
You ignore the zeros.
The padding here says one,
because t zero is what?
One and one is less than five, so that matches.
And then the second t four is 65 is less than six.
That's false.
That's set to zero.
What's really cool about this is that it only requires three instructions
to evaluate a single word.
It works with any word size.
As I said, these are apite.
Words can go larger.
It doesn't matter.
And all these different formulas here,
they're all defined in the paper.
They actually didn't invent these.
Actually,
leslie lamport event of these back in the 1970s to do this kind
of these bit wise comparisons.
So again, nothing i'm showing here is actually, SIMD,
this is just doing this mask here.
You can use regular 60instructions,
but you're still getting the parallelism because you pack things to fit a
in a single word.
Right?
This is pretty cool.
Again, the1970s, SIMD,
I think SIMD existed theoretically with flints taxonomy.
But I don't think any cpu back in the 70s supported this,
at least not to the extent they do now.
So again,
i'm showing you 8 bit words if you had 64 bit words.
Now you can pack in 16 free byte values,
and you can do this simple arithmetic to compute the comparison very quickly.
The question is,
why do they arrange vertically instead of horizontally next slide?
Because we have to at this point here,
we just have a one and a zero to say this match.
We've got to convert this back into what is the offset of the tuple.
And then it's raising horizontally will solve the problem.
You have one less bit to represent all of your data.
Say this does this mean?
You have one less bit to represent all your data,
but normally, the americans does the quest 32bits.
Now, it can't be put here because this would only be the 31bit.
If you had random third cube,
it ended as wouldn't this actually not work?
You'd have to know something about the value domain to say,
what's the minimum you can do?
Right?
This is why they're assuming they're dictionary encoded in order preserving.
So again, these are a bunch of,
say, the state codes in the united states.
You could represent that in these bits.
Let me plow ahead and get through to answer her question.
Yeah, these all are bit weaved packed.
I don't say packs.
That means that's compression scheme,
but these are bit maps.
We can just do all the same comparison that I showed in the last slide.
And we have a bunch of vectors like this.
Again, in our delimiter,
we have set 0to1 based on whether it matched.
But now we need to convert this back into,
again, whether what offset matched.
You just do simple bit shifting to slide things over based on where you are
in the list.
Then now when you combine these together,
then you end up with a bit map that says what tuple actually matched.
That's why you have to shift this t what t four was over here.
When I shifted it over by one,
when I push it up, it lands nicely where t four should be.
Is it more efficient?
A statement isn't the one we saw before more I the higher co encoding
or a bit slicing?
Is that more efficient for facing the word and the thing to do in the operation?
But not just do you have to face the way?
Is it?
The storage of the bit slicing approach is potentially more efficient.
I because our modeling is obviously,
yes, I want to reduce.
Yes, but this bit is not another bit,
but we're going to face the data as well.
Even if the data is a little bit small,
and it doesn't matter whether you're catching the 32 bits of the data as well.
Whereas in bit splicing, you're only fetching 1 bit for every 32bit.
You understand?
Ii had to look at the original paper.
I forget whether think it might have compared against bit slicing,
and this is way faster.
This is faster.
Yes.
Actually, the vertical one, we'll see next.
That's actually even faster.
That answers your question like why you shift it over and you pop it up.
And then that's why they do they arrange it that way.
This is called the selection vector.
This basically is a bit math that says that is the value for the does
the tube of this offset?
Did this match our predicate or not?
But again, it's just a bit map.
We've got to convert that back actually to numerical offsets.
Right?
There's two ways to do this.
One is the new real simple thing would just be take our selection vector
and just write a for loop and say,
if the bit set to one,
then I know this is the two ball at this offset.
I then I need to consider it'll work.
So the better approach is to do a precomputed positions table where you
recognize the size of my bit map.
Isn't that big?
In this case here, it's 8bits.
That means that there's only two to the eight possible combinations
of offsets that could be in this represented by this bit map.
I can just pre compute that as a giant array where the offset
of the integer of the integer representation of the bits corresponds
to an offset position table.
Then I have a pre computed vector of the two plus that match.
This is150.
I jump to one position, 150.
And there's my offsets.
And I can keep that this positions table,
it's in a low megs.
If that I keep this in ll two or l one,
this technique was amended by vector wise in the late2000s.
And then we end up using this in our own system for our research
on vectors and execution stuff.
Paper papers will cover a later semester.
All right.
This is the horizontal.
Sorry,
that's already in the register, right?
But iii got to go examine the bits.
There isn't an instruction that says convert these bits into the integers.
You just pre compute this little small table.
This is way faster.
This is the horizontal representation.
I don't, I don't know whether they actually implemented this in quick step.
No, the system I know, actually does this.
I just find this like super cool and super clever like the things you can do.
The vertical one is the one that showed up in the sketch paper.
You guys read same thing as before.
We're going to split our tuples up into segments or row groups.
But now what we're going to do is going to journey bit slices
for all the positions and store those continuously in memory.
Right?
Take all on the first column, on the second column, and the third column.
And each segment will store those bits.
In this case here, even though the second segment only has 2 tuples,
we had to store the entire bit map with much useless data,
because we had to make sure that everything fits in up.
In our process of words,
what can you do with this?
When we want to start doing evaluating two balls, we can use.
Now, SIMD,
to compare tuples, i'm sorry,
to compare bits on a bit by bit basis within the value that we're looking for.
Right along in sydney registers without having go to back
to regular cpu registers and compute our predicates very efficiently.
Say we have now select star from table with value equals two.
I'm showing over the inequality predicate,
just for simplicity, but you can use inequalities as well.
For this one, we're going to represent it in binary form, 010.
We want to do an evaluation of the first bit,
find all the matches within our first bit map vector.
In our first slice,
we throw out this empty zero mass thing.
We do our sympathy compare to see whether it's true.
And then we get back,
we get better a selected vector like this.
Right?
Then we have to evaluate the second one,
but we only want to compare the ones where we know that actually match
the first one.
It would be these positions here.
So we'd bring in another mask to do that comparison.
And then this would then produce out a in this case, they're all zeros.
We just use that pop count thing before when we look at the vector and say,
how many ones are there?
As soon as the vector comes out with all zeros,
we know we're done and we do early pruning.
Right?
So this is basically bit slicing,
but a way to do it with SIMD efficiently.
Right?
In the case,
in the horizontal coding, we can't do early pruning,
because we had to always look at the whole tuples,
the whole bits within the attribute or the value in this case here,
because we slice it up,
we can do early stops.
Is this different from this place?
It's just showing you how to do it with SIMD.
It's a statement.
You're doing this exact same operation as bit slicing.
Yes.
But like the visual bit slicing paper doesn't say how to do this.
The difference because it was from the90s.
Right?
In this case here, we're able to examine 8 tuples with two instructions.
That's insane.
It's amazing.
Again, if you had to do a sequential scan with a for loop and evaluate tuples one by one,
and there were attributes on the column.
You're not going to get down to it in two instructions.
It's not entirely true.
I it's two SIMD instructions,
but there's instructions to get things in and out of the registers.
You pay that cost.
But we're ignoring that for now,
right?
That's a lot.
Where have we gone so far?
We've done zone maps bit.
Map index is bit slicing, bit weaving.
Then we'll finish up quickly and talk about column imprints
and column sketches all the bit map schemes.
I showed you so far about storing exact representations of the data
within the columns.
Meaning, again,
I think the simplest case of the basic bit map index with the quality coding,
there's a one whether, in a bit map,
whether the value is equivalent or not.
Now, the range encoding, you're kind of grouping things together.
As I said, that's what basically sketching is trying to do.
But in a different way.
But in general, it's ignoring region coding.
If I could check a bit map,
and it says something it matches, I know it matches.
And i'll have to go double check on the actual tuple and make sure I
don't have false positives.
But in some cases,
if we give up some of this accuracy to support faster evaluation
and maybe more compact bit maps,
then that actually might be a big win for the common case.
Again, there's extreme examples as we talked about.
Those may not work perfectly for this,
but most data doesn't look like that.
Right?
Most data is highly skewed.
Again,
we may have to check original data in some cases to make
sure there's no false positives.
And the case of the range encoding example,
I always had to go check.
But in the sketch check, in some cases,
I know there will be some times where I don't have to check.
Column imprints is a precursor to the column sketches.
The basic idea is that we're going to have a bit map that says
whether something could exist.
It's basically collapsing down the bit slices into a single bit map
instead of multiple slices.
Same original data is184.
So i've had bit indexes like this.
You would see that like for the different possible values that I have,
there's a bunch of ones.
There's a bunch of columns or a bunch of bit maps that are zeros.
So instead, if I distort imprint,
I just collapse us all down by ordering everything.
Then I end up with a single bit map called an imprint.
I can use that to then determine whether quickly whether something exists
or not.
And again, if I get a one here or one over here,
I got to go check the original tuples and see whether it's
actually a match or not.
But if i'm landing maybe in here,
I knew this is a zero.
I don't have to do anything.
What's that?
It's like a balloon.
It's the same as it's like a bloom filter.
A without, I guess,
a any sort of false positive rate guarantees or things like that.
We'll cover bloom filters much more detail when we talk about hash joins,
but basically the same idea.
Good.
Looking at digesting glen column and print slides.
Yeah.
This was done and this was done in mooney to be again in the early 2000s tense.
The column sketch paper you guys read is a variation, as I said,
a bit map range, encoded bit maps,
where the idea is that we want to maintain aa sketch,
which is,
this is like a probabilistic data structure, kind of like a bloomboat.
There's county sketches and things like that.
But it's an approximation of what data exists.
And it's gonna be the bit will be set the true to determine that there is something,
it could be something in this range.
The idea is that we want to convert our are sort of base values
into these smaller codes.
And then we would use those codes to figure out how much data we
actually have to look at.
Now,
there's going to be a trade off between the distribution of the values
and the compactness.
If our codes are the same size of the original data,
then they're going to be very precise.
Of course,
that means that we're not going to a throw anything away and waste space
for maintaining using the values twice.
They will have a special case for the most frequent values to avoid false positives,
because otherwise,
if something appears all the time,
and they get sort of grouped together, you may have to go,
we check to see whether the thing actually exists or not.
But if you have a special case,
I know this frequent value appears most 99% of the time.
Here is the exact value for it.
I can just do that look ups and avoid having to go read things I don't need.
Here's a high level overview how it works.
Say we have our original data,
and we're storing this as aa bit values.
What they're going to do is basically take a pass over the data.
Again.
We can do this.
If we're we're creating an immutable file,
we've got to read everything in and encode it and write it out.
So they can build a histogram where they want the height of the data
represented within a range of the histogram within a bucket to be
equivalent.
You want the you don't have one range,
have a lot of skew.
And therefore, you're doing much of look ups on it for useless data.
It's then based on this histogram, again,
the paper sort of describes how you'd actually want to build it.
You maintain this compression map.
The idea is that you would say within this,
the values over here,
it's less than a greater, less than or equal to this.
You get mapped to some smaller dictionary code here.
Then now, when you want to return this column as in the sketch form,
you want to store these in these codes here.
Instead of actually original values,
say the original values were 8 bits.
I can store it now down into 2 bits.
Now, when a query comes along,
like select star from table,
where value is less than 90,
I do a look up in my map and figure out what's the highest
the smallest value that will be covered by the thing i'm looking for.
In this case here, 90 is greater than 60.
I got to go to the next 11. 30 2 is greater than 90.
So I can stop here.
I know I need to consider the values that are encoded by these code values here.
You basically convert you use the mapping function to convert 90 into 01.
And then I go do a look up in my ii know these are the offsets that
are matching for me in my sketch column.
But because 132,
132is greater than 90.
We don't know whether there might be a value like 91,
92 that doesn't satisfy our predicate,
but is still within the scope that's managed by this code value here.
For zero ones,
we have to go back to the original data and see whether we have
a false positive or not.
So in this case here,
but 01.2,
the code 01 points to 81~140. 81will satisfy our predicate.
140does not.
There is tactical call error here,
because 132 means that like 01 is in the range of 60~132,
01can't map to 140,
140should map to 10, isn't it?
As a typo?
That's my fault.
Did I screw this up?
Apply?
I might have typed that wrong.
That's my fault.
So i'd say this is hundred 20,
the type that's the type of in direction that we have to go out of.
So it's, david,
doesn't this have the same problem as before?
Where?
Or in direction in terms of traversing the data structure itself
or actually doing this?
Second, look up over here.
Second,
you had one for me that you were going to now.
Or do you put up all of them together and do it?
Yeah.
So his statement is,
when I talked about the hierarchical encoding,
I talked about how like i've got to go up and down the tree to go find
all the bits that was just trying to find the matches from the bits,
like when they were set to one,
then I go look out and get the actual two balls themselves in the table.
In this case here,
I can scan through this column quickly,
find all the positions where it's either 0001.
Then for the ones that are 01,
it depends on what the query actually needs.
I then do my batch look up to go get the actual look at the exam
and the actual the data itself.
You would scan this thing first,
get all the offsets.
You could use ap community table.
If you want it to, it doesn't matter.
Get all the offsets where this that where it satisfies my code,
where it's less than or equal to 01.
I've got to maybe get the data anyway, because in this case here,
it's like star.
I've got to go get all the values anyway.
Then I do an extra check there before I shut up to the next operator
and the query plan.
Other than the type of the abbey picked out.
Thank you.
Any questions about this?
Isn't the main optimization that if it isn't on that boundary, but the 01,
is it 00 you're going to have to do?
The his statement is one of the organizations you would get is
I only have to check for 01 to avoid false positives.
And in case it's 00,
I don't have to go check it again,
like depends on what the query is.
If it's a count, then I go check these,
but I count it all together.
If I need to do like a join where I do need, maybe the column,
I had to go fetch it anyway,
but I don't have to do the comparison because I know it satisfies my predicate.
All right, cool.
And on time,
those amounts, as I said,
are the most widely used method to accelerate sequential scans.
It's pretty much what everyone will give you.
I think parquet actually,
I know my work and this is what parquet the only thing parquet has.
Bit map indexes are more common in the sort of the enterprise row stores honestly.
Postcards lessons themselves enterprise,
but I like the oracles and sql servers,
things that cost a lot of money.
Because again,
they were trying to get the benefits of sort of columnar processing or data
without having to to have a whole columnist or engine,
which they all eventually built anyway.
As I said,
we're completely ignoring multi dimensional indexes and vertical indexes.
I don't think they teach a 26 anymore,
but that whole class was about this kind of stuff.
Kd trees are trees and so forth.
We can ignore that geo spatial things.
We ignore that.
And then our verte index is just like a mapping from a word or an n graham
within a text field to the extra tuples that match.
Next class.
We'll talk about data compression.
We'll spend most of the time talking about tuples.
We'll also talk about how we actually compress these bit maps
as well beyond the things we talked about before.
So quickly, I want to talk about project one, which is out,
thank you for win for updating everyone at piazza.
So for the first project,
you guys will be writing a foreign data wrapper for postcards to access,
to access the columnar data stored in a file format that we invented.
The reason why we didn't choose parquet or work
because there's existing libraries to access them,
and they basically care of all the complexity for you.
And it's way more complicated, also bring it in these other libraries.
So we just gave you something really simple and hear about that.
A foreign data rapper is basically a way to have if you're
from your sequel light,
it's got a virtual table.
It's a way to basically sometimes called a connector.
But it's basically it's a way to have lincoln a shared object to postgres
that allows you override
scan operators on a table to go to whatever that shared object wants to support,
rather than always go into their internal base tables.
There's foreign data wrappers to read csv files,
foreign data wrapper to read.
We connect to another database system, right?
Postcards is actually really extensible.
It's very amazing.
It's an amazing,
it's amazing data system, but it's also very extensible,
which is pretty cool.
So there's actually commercial products that build foreign data wrappers
for postcards,
like time scale is makes heavy use of this.
But again,
from the sql perspective, it looks like a regular table,
even though it's going to go through your code.
The goal of this is get you familiar with how to extend progress,
because you could use that for project three,
but also to actually implement the things that we're talking
about in class today in the last couple classes of how she had a scan
through kilometer data.
The file format that when developed pretty basic,
we're not doing any compression.
It's just storing things in columnar data and columnar format.
Sorry,
the footer has jason metadata about where to find the offsets
for different types of data.
I bumped the deadline up.
I don't know.
I think it was due the 16th or something.
And now it's due to the 26th, which is a sunday.
And all the information is on the project website now.
And then i'll post on piazza,
a spreadsheet.
So I I already know everyone's andrew idi i'm gonna fill out a form to get
aws credits.
Then i'll send everyone an email.
If you're enrolled in the class code for like $100 from amazon,
you can use that for development.
If you want.
You use it for bit coin mining.
Go ahead, I don't care.
So anyway, like we you can make it work on your laptop,
make it work on ec two.
An end of the day has to compile and work on aws sorry,
i'm on grade school.
This is how you submit this.
Again, we've already provided you a basic file format.
There's instructions on what it actually looks like.
It's not super sophisticated.
It's not doing any compression.
It's literally just storing data in binary form and in common and common arrangement.
So the first step you want to do is just write a parse over this file,
just to scan image of columns and try to stitch two balls back together.
When you process when you read the metadata,
I understand what the offsets are.
Know how to put tuples back together.
Then you want to integrate this in postgres in using the foreign data wrapper,
api I think when we provide them some basic skeleton code already, right?
There's some basic skeleton code,
some functions you've got to fill out,
and then instructions on the website how to actually compile and then link
it into postgres.
And then the last step is then you want to actually support predicate evaluation.
So you can have postgres,
take the where clause.
We're not trying to support all everything you can possibly do in a where clause,
some basic comparison operators that'll get passed to you in what the post
got struck.
And you want to then apply the predicate as you scan the data.
You have to join us.
It's hard.
It was surprisingly difficult enough just to do the scan.
As a foreign driver.
I suppose I say process is extensible.
That's great.
I never said it's easy to extend.
You can't extend it, right?
The way to get started, as I said, start with the this,
Writing the parcel code without any post graphs.
You can just do that locally.
You should do this in c plus,
and we're giving you skeleton code that uses pgxs if you want to do rust,
talk to chi.
He's gonna tell you go away, but like you looked into it, right?
Or Wayne looked at it.
We don't think you can do it.
But you he can do it because because he's all right.
Offering that out.
All right?
So just like the interclass,
make sure you all your button locally,
you write your own local tests,
don't use gray scope to do this,
because it's going to be slow.
Don't change any of the files that we don't other than the ones that use
the on grade scope,
because those will get wiped one compile and link it on grade scope.
Make sure you fork our version of progress,
because it already has the scaffolding code that win has set up.
And it's all sort of set up for you to like compile from the command line
or vs code or whatever sea line he's using.
That's in there.
And then it'll be able to link it in.
You don't have to figure that out yourself, which is not trivial.
And then please post questions on piazza or come to piazo office hours.
Ok.
There are example,
farm data rappers that are in the write up that Wayne is linked to.
There's the parquet one,
and then it's the slightest one.
Some of the scaffolding code will look very similar.
It won't be entirely useful to you,
but you can just look at it as a reference, but avoid copying wholesale.
Without attribution from existing cute,
you may find and also, too,
because there's always random people on the internet that see the videos
and try to implement themselves,
avoid their stuff.
It's usually crap.
I'm not going to lie,
right?
Any questions?
Ha ha, that's my favorite.
All that are.
What is it?
It's the SP cricket,
idesi make a mess unless I could do it like a deal,
ice cube with the g to the e to the t it comes.
Do I play the game?
Where's no roof?
He's on the custody.
I'm a focus on drink fruit,
put the bus a cap on the ice road,
bush week on the go with a blow to the eyes come.
Indeed,
that's me rolling with 5th what's up park and south central g and thank us
when I party.
By the 12 pack case on the 46 pack,
48 gets the real Paris.
I drink fruit, but you are drinking Bob 12,
but they say bill makes you fat,
but saying eyes is straight,
so it really don't matter.