Hey, yo, yo,
pack the chrome sounds by like mrs.
Jones, liverpool mathematics.
We have the devil spoken stone.
Up one heads,
the bed make shot some little when we get started for chat up,
everyone can down with us this beginning.
I'll get two people in new york city easy, evan,
and then brooklyn dva is the finest jail in seattle and they put the greek.
These people that are helping us out and staying true to us.
Since the beginning.
I want to thank carnegie mellon for not firing me for another year.
That's always important.
The core sponsor for this semester is going to be amazon.
Amazon is the largest database vendor in the world in terms of market cap,
how much money they're making.
Right?
They make all the money on the store,
make a lot of money aws but they make a ton of money on databases.
Redshift aurora or the dynamo db they have a ton of stuff.
Usually oracle was number one.
Actually, maybe microsoft is number one for a while, too.
Amazon is officially number one as of which microsoft might be number 100,
whatever they're making a ton of money.
Anyway, they're helping us with the course logistics and sponsor goes.
We're really appreciative of that.
And then the end of the semester,
somebody will come give from the redshift team come and give a tech talk
about the system that they're building.
We will discuss redshift throughout the semester.
A lot of the techniques that will describe during the semester
they're actually implementing in their system.
I quickly want to go over the course logistics and what the expected
for the semester,
but I must have had most of the time on the history of databases,
because I find that part more interesting.
And then as I sent the email out over the weekend,
it would be based on the two readings.
Again, it's not meant to be like deep into the internal of data systems.
Just to give you perspective of what the landscape looks like,
why we're spending all the time talking
about relational databases and not other things.
So a lot of you guys are here for obvious reasons you want to take this course.
But just as the final pitch,
i'll say the things that we talk about this semester for database systems
and particularly for analytical database systems,
these are hard problems not ever can do it.
And companies pay a lot of money for students,
not coming to this class from other places as well that have experience
in working database systems.
If you're just a random javascript programmer,
they're not going to be touching davis and turtles same way.
They're not going to be touching the kernel in an operating system, right?
They don't want people off the street.
They want people to understand fundamentally how these systems are working.
These are the things that we're going to cover.
This is not the full list,
but these are just some of the former students that have worked with us
in taking this class and places that they've gone.
These are the ones I have photos a there's way more than i'm missing,
but these are the ones that I I could quickly find.
Three of them are with me at my startup at autogen,
some of the best ones as well.
All right.
So the unlike in previous years where you try to cover
maybe in memory database systems,
and spend a little time discussing transaction systems,
this semester, we're only going to focus on analytical database systems,
just because this is sort of what the hot thing is right now.
And there's a lot of money sloshing around a lot of systems being built.
And to sort of understand we want to understand what the state of the art
is and how we got to the point where we are today.
The goal for you guys is that not only we become aware of what
these systems actually are.
What are the key features about them and help you to sort of understand
the trade offs between one system design or implementation versus
another?
You'll hopefully also become proficient in writing high quality systems code,
right?
Doing documentation and testing and doing code reviews.
Right?
These are soft skills that can be important when you go out in the real world,
new systems development,
that it's not something like there's any class to say,
here's how to write documentation.
Here's how to write test code.
It's just things you sort of have to pick up as you go along.
The projects will be designed such that you'll get exposure to these sort
of best practices on how to do these to work on data systems.
This course, also, too, is only going to cover state of the art topics.
I'm assuming everyone has taken a database class,
either last semester or four forty five six, 45.
What you're undergrad like,
we're not going to go over to the basic of what a join is, right?
Talk,
we assume how to do a hash join.
We'll talk about how to do it parallel and do it, make it run fast.
The topics that we're going to cover.
First start off talking about storage models and compression.
And actually, how do you represent data in files on disk?
Then we'll talk about how to do query execution using sort
of modern techniques like vectorization and compilation.
Then we'll talk about modern join algorithms.
Networking protocols are getting things out of the data in and out of the database.
Then we'll spend a little time talking about how to do query optimization,
go much deeper than we were able to cover in the inter class.
If you look at the schedule,
the last four or five lectures are actually targeting single database systems.
There's a whole lecture on snowflake, a whole lecture on data bricks,
a whole lecture on big query of drama.
The idea is that we want to take all the things we discussed
throughout the semester,
understand the basics of them,
and then look at a real system that implements all these things.
And try to understand like, why are they doing this a certain way?
Or what are the benefits?
Or what are the disadvantages of the approaches that they're taking?
Again, i'm assuming you've taken an intro davis class.
We're not going to cover sort of the basics of sql and other things.
So all the website is up to date.
I I haven't updated the homepage because I try to get,
I try to use dolly to have like the last supper and in the middle,
it didn't work out very well.
I've got to work on it anyway.
So the website is up to date.
So the syllabus and the schedule is all there.
For the most part, it's stable.
So if you understand what's expected for you in the course,
please go look at that.
I'll say this throughout a couple of times in the beginning, right?
For academic honesty,
again, this is the advanced level class.
I assume everyone here is smart.
Therefore, you don't need to cheat.
If you do cheat, we will take you over to warner hall and deal with that.
If you went in doubt,
if you're not sure about doing something like I have
this little stupid code that somebody wrote in get hub,
can I use it in my project?
If you're not sure,
then just ask myself at the ta my office hours to be mondays and wednesdays,
the hour before class,
upstairs on the line floor.
And then we can talk about anything you want,
any of the projects and papers.
How to get a database job?
I have a bunch of database shirts.
My office, the company send me.
Please come and get some,
because i'm kind of getting a little hoarder level because they send
a bunch of me during the pandemic.
I have a bunch of boxes.
I've got to start getting rid of them.
So come and talk to me.
We have one ta when he's awesome.
So he's my third year ph student.
This is true.
He is a former paralegal for like the sketchy law firm.
He is a certified chicken farmer.
He is the number of ranked phd student at carnegie mellon for data
for databases to be very clear.
So, again, he'll help me with the projects.
He'll be a part of the conversations as we go along the semester.
So by all means, leverage him.
If you have questions.
The expectations are 33 things.
There's reading assignments, projects, and the final exam.
Every class will have one assigned reading,
except for today's class.
And they'll be indicated by the icon here.
I'll post on piazza what's actually expected in in these in these reading reviews.
But the main ideas ii want you to get out of is like, read the paper,
understand what they're doing,
understand all the things that we talked about,
how to put, how would it fit together in a higher system,
a higher level system.
Then.
I'm also curious.
I don't understand what are the workloads that you to evaluate
the the implementation for analytical databases.
It's most likely going to be tpch and tpcds over and over again.
It's good just to know what these things are,
so that when we go into project one, project two, actually, or project three,
you'll have an idea of what workloads you can use based
on the papers you've read.
And there's a google form here that is live,
and then there will be a drop down.
You fill that out.
Yes?
It should be three.
You can skip three readings.
Sorry, i'll fix that.
Thank you.
Again, all these reviews have to be your own writing.
Some of these papers are pretty stated.
They are like they came out last week,
and so they're probably not going to be a review on the internet.
You can use.
You could try chat gpt see what happens.
Project one, we'll post next week.
But you'd be basically writing a foreign data wrapper for post graphs,
process, columnar data format, like a parquet file.
The idea here is just to expose you to how to do vectors execution
in the context of post graphs.
So we don't worry about do sql parsing.
We don't worry about doing query planning.
Let postcards handle all that.
And the idea here would be that you'd be able to trade see the tradeoffs
between your sort of custom engine on the column and our data
versus post stresses,
row based iterator model.
Again, what i'm saying, does it make sense?
Then that's not good because we cover these things in the interclass,
but make sure at least go back and look at them and understand what
i'm talking about.
Again, we'll post this next week.
Project two is going to be writing an article for encyclopedia,
so we have an encyclopedia of databases.
So every single database that i'm aware of the idea would be,
you go look at the documentation, go read,
maybe even run these systems,
go talk to the developers,
understand how they're implementing these different parts of the system
that we care about.
And you'll be writing article for this.
Ok?
Don't plagiarize with this,
avoid marketing language.
Sometimes I give the company's access to the website,
and they'll say, like my database is the fastest whatever, right?
And we have to remove all that.
Only say things that you can back up by specific claims.
Right?
We more care about the internal and not like how people feel
about the database if that makes sense.
Project three will be a group project.
And the idea here would be some larger topic that you're interested in.
That's based on the things we're discussing throughout the semester.
It doesn't have to be in postgres, but if you want,
it can be.
The idea here is that you just want to build something that exhibits
some understanding of mastery of the materials we discussed
throughout those masters.
Again, i'll post some topics as we get closer.
You want to decide later until march.
What do you exactly want to do?
I have some ideas of things that I want to do.
That could potentially turn into a short paper,
or like a capturing project.
Again, we can discuss these as we go along.
Again, don't plagiarize.
And all your code has to be your code you submit to us has to be
yours unless you discuss and attributed same thing for the encyclopedia.
Please don't just copy from the from random things on internet.
1 year somebody copied from wiki pda and they had like a little
like there's the text and then the square bracket and then the number
for the citation.
So we had to go deal with that again.
So the reason why i'm keep showing this because this is on video now.
Because then if you guys do plagiarize,
and then I go to turn you in.
I show them the video link on youtube, or like, here's me discussing this.
And you're screwed.
There'll be a final exam, but it'll be take home.
Long form questions.
I did try chat gbt and it was not able to answer them.
So who knows whether how much better that will get?
So it's either that like,
I wonder if it's a limitation of chat gbt or whether my questions are just terrible.
And it can't parse them acting with you is like really bad at like kind
of like specialized questions like you can answer
basic computer science questions really well,
but once you dealt with the specialist you kind of like drops the ball
but like terribly but it phrases an amber.
So you think it's right,
it's like multi version current control is important because it
does multiversioning like thanks.
That's what it told me.
Right?
Grey breakdown is like this.
Again, this is on the syllabus,
no big surprises here.
And then the chorus mailing list, everything will be on piazza.
If you have any technical questions as about project
one and potentially project three,
as we go along.
Please post on piazza.
Don't email one of myself directly.
And if anything else like your health issues,
whatever you have going on,
please email directly.
Any questions about this?
Let's get to this databases.
Yeah.
1 year somebody complained on youtube.
I you spent 25 minutes discussing logistics of the course,
get to the good stuff.
So here we are.
As I said,
this is sort of my bridge history of the last 50,
60 years of databases.
So we're not going to go too deep into any one topic,
but it's a going to an overview of the lay of the land that like,
I think what's actually really interesting about this is that databases are
a hot area right now in both research and in in industry.
And yet they're 60 years old.
First one is going to be from the 1960s.
Right?
It just shows you how important they are and how hard the problem is.
If like,
it's clearly not a solved problem.
It's gonna this lecture sort of derived from two papers.
The first one was called what goes around comes around and is written
by mike stern bakker and joe hellers stein in 2006.
And it's basically mikes assessment of the database industry and how he
was right for the last 40 years.
Mike won the touring award in 2014,
so I would agree with him.
Then the paper, this other one draft I sent you.
This is mike.
And I wrote this last year where we basically looked at where this paper
left off and said what's the next sixteen seventeen years
And this was actually triggered by me,
because there was some like postman hacker news or somebody's like,
I don't know why people keep using relational databases.
Graph database is the way to go.
And I was like, all right,
I said that the mic, let's write the new ones.
The major take away.
What you guys get from this is that again,
even though databases are really old,
the concept is really old.
They are highly relevant today,
because the other day, every application,
what are they essentially doing?
Right?
They're exposing some user interface for for either a human
or another machine or something to interact with a database.
Right?
What's going to be interesting is a lot of the things that will cover this semester.
These are not new ideas.
They're not new concepts.
I'm going to see, I said this in andrew class.
I'll keep saying this over and over again throughout the semester.
Ibm did a lot of this stuff in the 1970s.
Just obviously, the harbor was much different.
The landscape was much different,
but a lot of the things we'll talk about will be just modern incarnations
of what ibm invented.
The years ago,
we're going to spend a whole lecture on query compilation,
how to take a segal query,
turn into a query plan and then converted that query plan into machine code.
Ibm did that in the 1970s.
It was system r they did it in an assembly.
Now we use lbm but again, the techniques are not new.
The other big thing is going to happen and you'll see this the rest
of your life is that every 10 years somebody's gonna come along and say,
hey, sequel is stupid.
Relational model that's slow, right?
We can do it better.
Here's my new data system that doesn't use, at least the model is equal.
Right?
Everyone's gonna go excited like this is the future sql
is old,
sequel is busted, we don't want to use that.
And then low and behold people realize the relational model was
a good idea or sql
is a good idea.
Either that thing that the new invention that comes along,
either that fails,
or the whatever ideas that this new idea,
this new concept or new data system has letters get adopted
by the sequel standard and by the racial model.
Then that thing goes away.
All right?
So I think i've seen this in my own life,
like no sequel is a hot thing.
People said sequel slow, sequel, stupid,
relation models too, but you want to do documents,
you need jason and everybody built all these jason databases.
Right?
And then now we're at the point where maybe that's a bad idea for everything.
Json is good for some things.
The relation model now supports json.
And then all the no sql systems that said sql is a bad idea.
Every one of them except for redis supports sql,
right?
Mongo support to see last year.
Right?
So you're going to see this throughout the theme,
as we go along is that at least once we get past and once the racial model
gets invented,
people will say every 10 years it's stupid.
And then it turns out it was mark my board and you'll see this the rest
of your life.
I guarantee you,
let's start at the very beginning,
1960s.
So to the best of my knowledge,
at least what is considered conventional wisdom,
the very first database system,
our sort of general purpose database system,
was this thing called integrated data store or iids and I say general purpose,
what I mean is that it was a database system that was designed to support
arbitrary data sets or databases.
Right?
Obviously,
you can write a little python application yourself and read and write files.
That's just for exactly that one database.
That's not what I mean by this, like those things sort of existed.
But this was specifically to say we could then reuse the system
for another application or another customer.
Ge got this for.
It was like some timber company out of seattle that had
a huge inventory tracking problem that they need to deal with.
And said they built this thing called ids to handle that.
They end up spinning it out of that custom solution for the timber company
and try to sell it a as a standalone product.
Right?
Like ge was trying to be a software vendor.
Is ge the hot thing in computers right now?
No.
Right.
So what the huge mistake they did is that they had this company policy
at the time where ge said,
if we're not number one in some industry,
we don't want to be in it at all.
So they were like the number three computer seller that wasn't good
enough for them.
And so they sold off their computing division to honeywell.
Right?
Then honeywell owned own owned ids and then they were sort of selling it
for a while.
So there could be two key things about ids that are going to be bad ideas
that are going to then get fixed in their relation to model.
The first is to meet this network data model,
and i'll explain what that is in a second.
And then the other one's going to be this notion of the tuple at a time query,
meaning like i'm going to write,
basically for loops in my program,
iterate over one tuple at a time and do something.
But as we know, in sql, though,
we're an operator or bags or sets,
we declare what the thing we actually want to do.
That then could apply to multiple tuples.
And that's me way more efficient.
So ids didn't really take off as far as I know.
But what actually came out of the project was this thing called codacil.
I I should do a survey before the class starts.
Who's ever heard of coda still?
Well, who not from the previous class?
One of you code is always going to be the hot thing of databases.
This was the thing that everyone's going to build for their database.
And obviously, we don't.
So there was this guy, charles bachman,
who worked in ids and he saw,
she saw the need for having a standard way for cobalt programmers
to interact with the database system.
They proposed this data model and this query api called codes film
that incorporated the network data model from and the tube
out of time query model from the previous slide from ids and they said
this is
going to be the standard going forward.
So then bachmann left ids and he worked at this thing called que lane,
which has been bought and sold over many years.
And he helped build a new version of a network data model based
on code cell called idms and this thing is actually still around today.
You're obviously, if you're a brand new startup, you wouldn't use this,
right?
This is for like legacy applications.
So the networking model is going to look like this.
So say I have this example where i'm say i'm nasa.
This is actually a real example.
I'm nasa and i'm building a rocket for the go to the moon
by the apollo moon mission.
A it's a huge engineering project.
I need to keep track of all the parts that are going to my rocket
and what manufacturer or what company can provide them for me.
Right?
So they would have this database where you have suppliers and the parts.
Then you keep track of what supplier can provide certain parts
and what price and what size and so forth.
Under the network data model,
you would have the high level entities like you would have a supplier,
the name of the company that could provide the part or provide parts.
You have the part that you need.
And then you have this other set that says,
here's the for this supplier,
they will supply this part, this price.
So you could have these high level entities.
But then you would have to implicitly have these sets.
Here what i'm showing in italics, right?
You would have the supplies and the supplied by,
you would say I have a supplier and there will be a supply
that's in the set of supplies.
Now if I want to find find me all the parts that a supplier supplies,
I would have to do a bunch of nest of four lips.
Go look over every supplier here,
look over all their supply sets,
get the supply types, and then reverse go back up there, right?
You basically write a bunch of these nets of four lips,
and you're doing this over one tube at a time.
Another problem is going to be is that actually,
the way you sort of look like this,
if you actually have an instance of this,
right?
You have supplier supplies of parts,
and then you would have these auxiliary tables
and basically cross reference tables you would have,
or you keep pointers to the actual objects.
And so these red lines i'm drawing here.
These are actually pointers like physical pointers to like,
here's the location of this record on disk or in memory.
Right?
Again.
So now, when you get your looping through,
try to find all the suppliers apply a certain part.
You'd have to look at the first one,
and then you do a look up to find the record in this entity.
And i'm going to call it a table because it's not.
And then you would follow the pointer to jump here.
And then potentially,
you could have a pointer to go back in the other direction.
Right?
So the queries are very complex, right?
This is all written in cobalt.
And it was less efficient because again,
you're operating over a single tuple at a time.
It was easily corruptible.
So if this thing gets if this the harbor is crappy back,
then this supplies or supplied by these collections of data,
these pointers.
If this thing gets corrupted,
your whole database is host,
because now you have no way to to traverse and find things,
understand the relationships between these objects.
All right.
So the next big system that was in the 1960s was this thing called ims
and this actually was built for the apollo moon mission.
Ibm was responsible for the building out of database to keep track
of all the parts they were.
Nasa was buying to build the rockets.
And again,
just like for ge and is they built a sort of custom database system
for the project and then realized it was useful for other customers,
and they spun it out as a separate product.
This thing still exists today.
And ibm makes a ton of money on these things.
And this data has been till today.
If you ever used an atm machine or anything in the bank,
a lot of them are still using ims as they set up in the 70s.
If it's not broken,
don't fix it.
Ims is going to use what's called a hierarchical data model.
And just like the network data model is going to use a tube out of time queries.
Then another big thing is that it's going to support a programmer to find
physical data structures,
meaning like if I have a collection of data like a table,
I don't use your table because they wouldn't call it that,
but assume it's a table.
I would actually tell the database system.
I want to store it as a hash table,
or I want to store it as ab plus tree.
Then based on what I told it,
I wanted to store it as you then got a different api that allowed you
traversing the data,
because you can't do range queries and hash tables,
but you can't do it on b plus trees.
Go back to our example here.
We have a supplier now.
I'm an idiot because this i'm leaving plug of a clicker in.
That's pathetic.
Right?
So I have a supplier.
And now they have parts that looks a little bit better, right?
Because now I don't have to have all this extra stuff.
Now,
but I do have an implicit relationship between explicit relation
between the supplier and the part.
A part can only supply by one particular supplier.
Right now, if I go to my instance,
right?
Say this first vendor,
they supply batteries.
I would have to have another whole record for that.
And then I would have to have another record for the second vendor
who's playing maybe the same batteries,
but a different price.
So let's say now if I change the name of the of the part from batteries to
on a brand name battery,
whatever I want to change this field here,
i've got to go through and change every single record instance
of where the batteries exist.
Because you were basically repeating information because you couldn't have
one part be supplied by multiple suppliers in this model.
The other problem you're going to have, also, too, is,
as I said about the,
since the system exposes the the ability to tell how you
actually want to store data,
a hash table versus b cluster or whatever,
then if I changed my mind and I said I sorted the hash table,
but I want to do range queries.
Let me switch it to ab plus tree.
You had no way of easily changing that.
You had to actually dump the data out,
then load it back under the new data structure.
Then you actually have to go update your application code,
because now it expose the hash the b plus gapi instead of the hash table
api there's no independence between the physical layer
and the logical layer what the data actually was.
All this is sort of the, yes,
the system didn't support it with ims now in like twenty, 2003.
I I ai think they have asql veneer on top of it.
Right?
And ii think it still is a hard come on an e there was attempts to convert
it to racial model in the 80s rented pin out.
But I this is like 1960s.
This is the way.
So this is the motivation for the relational model.
In the late 1960s,
there's this guy ted cod, who just finished his phd in math.
He was working in ibm research,
and he saw all of these ims programmers spending a lot of time rewriting
for application code over and over again,
because of this tight coupling between,
again, the physical layer and the logical layer.
And so then he realized that,
which is actually quite prescient that this is not scalable.
Humans at some point, it could be way more expensive than computers.
At the time computers are super expensive, humans are cheap.
The opposite now, right?
I can get an amazon instance,
a fraction of a penny an hour,
but a program is going to cost me 200 k how happens?
Just continue lecture,
not that one.
What?
Now i'm curious,
I don't know.
Are you laughing at the 200 k for database programmer?
That's a bit low?
Anyway, data programs aren't cheap,
but at the time it was slept,
he saw all these people wasting their time over again,
rewriting the application.
They saw the inefficiency of having this sort of two po at a time
programming api the relational model has sort of three key parts to it,
that again,
it serves as the background for all the racial modern racial data systems today.
The first of that,
we're going to store the database in simple data structures
instead of this graph in the coder cell network model,
or this hierarchy under ims we're going to store tables relations.
So these single heap things.
And if they have relations or if there are references to other tables,
we just store that as again as another attribute in their relations.
Right?
No need to have explicit pointers to anything.
The program is the way we're going to access the database
through a high level language.
Instead of writing these nested for loops,
they'll be able to say he didn't vent sequel at the time,
but I sorry,
there was not a programming language like siegel at the time,
but he had this idea like, ok,
there's a way to abstract what the actual physical materialization
of the physical structure of the database system.
And to say this is the answer I want.
And then a data system could figure it out for you.
Right?
And then this also now means that because I have this abstraction
between the physical layer and the logical layer,
the the strategy just stored the data physically on disk or in memory,
we left entirely up to the implementation.
Because based on what the queries wanted to do,
it could decide here's the best way to store your data.
Right?
The first paper on the racial model came out in 1969.
This is the very first one.
This is usually the one everyone cites as the
as the de facto relational model paper that this came out in the cacm
in 1970.
But this was the very first one.
We go back to our example before suppliers and supplies and parts.
Right?
It looks like this.
It's essentially what the network model was,
but now I don't have these explicit membership sets.
Then now if I want to sort of in a table or in tables in a relational database,
right now,
I have these foreign key references that are just attributes in the object.
And the data system can understand that this supplier number corresponds
to some supplier number in this other table here.
We'll get to c equal to second,
but this was a radical idea.
A sequel is a radical idea.
Now we take it for granted because it's so prevalent,
but back then the criticism of the relational model was there's no way
a database of no way a piece of software.
It's going to write queries as efficient as what a human can write.
This seems sort of strange,
but it's sort of the same argument that people made back in the day,
that there's no way a compiler could generate program code that is
more efficient than what a human could write.
Sure that's potentially true for like highly skilled and embedded systems programmers.
But nobody writes assembly today.
Right?
Everybody writes in higher level languages and even higher like up in python.
But back then, again, this is like the sea compiler came out in 1970.
This was an insane idea and turned out it was correct.
The depends on the implementation of the query optimizer, how good it is.
And we'll see some papers that show how things go wrong.
And that's certainly a hard problem.
But in general,
like a database system is going to generate a more efficient query plan
than an average programmer could actually write.
And also,
now it exposes the data system to people that are maybe art programmers,
like business analysts or people doing accounting reporting, right?
But they are not hardcore programmers.
They can write sql, but maybe not can't write any cc plus.
So ted cod put out the paper in 1970.
He was a mathematician,
this paper here, it's actually not the hard to read.
But when you read the criticisms of it or people talk about it at the time
contemporary conversations about it,
people say it was inscrutable.
It was told was heavy on math,
not.
But again, maybe 1970s, I don't know, maybe it was.
He didn't propose a programming language in that paper.
He later did in 1974, 75,
this thing called alpha didn't go anywhere.
But it was all math at the time.
And he didn't actually build a system to prove that his idea was working
could work.
What happened was there was a bunch of people saw his paper,
said, hey,
I think this is a good idea and actually started building
experimental systems to test that out.
The very first system that i'm aware of that did was this thing called
the peter lee relational test vehicle,
which sounds like a 1970s, like druggie ban.
But these are like people in the uk that basically read his paper, like,
I think it's a good idea.
And they built sort of early prototypes from four sequel.
It they talk about,
it could store massive data sets of like 1,002 poles like that was mind
blowing for them back of them.
That one usually people forget about.
That's far as I know, that's the very first one.
But there's two other projects that came1 or 2 years after system are at
ibm and then ingress at berkeley.
These are considered the very first to relational data systems that
like try to or try to build something based on ted cards work
and actually build a real system.
I think mimer sequel came out at a sweden,
maybe a 1 or 2 years later,
but this is an act on a project.
This still exists today.
Oracle with larry ellison, we know about that.
And we'll cover that throughout the semester.
Basically,
the it's all happening in silicon valley.
Larry elsin basically copy what ibm did.
He would literally call them on the phone and ask about like,
how does this work?
And they would tell them because they were researchers didn't know,
and he went and copied it.
And then ingress eventually got commercialized at the university
in the late 70s,
because people actually started really using it because they understood
the the certificates of the racial model.
But again, 1970s, it was not clear that it could have been coda, still,
it could have been a relational model.
Eventually in the 1980s, relational model, one,
two things happened, three things happened.
First is that ibm never commercialized system are they could have been
a dominant player in the and they do this marketplace,
but they drop the baldness because they were making so much money on ims like,
why would you kill the golden goose with this other new data system that
may not work when you're making so much money on ims but eventually they
saw the light and they put out their
first relational database system called segal ds in 1981,
this had remnants of system r but a lot of it was written from scratch.
Sequel.
Ds is still around.
They renamed it to db two,
just like dv two for vse there's some like mainframe system that they wrote
sql ds four.
There's five versions of db two.
It's hard to track of them.
But then what we know about what we consider db two today,
that first came out in 1983.
When this came out 83,
this is sort of the shot across the bow in the database industry to say,
now ibm series by the relational model.
These is a real idea.
Ingress and oracle are already still in the marketplace.
But it basically showed that the relation model is the way forward.
And sequel became the defective standard when this came out in 83.
And oracle was at the right place at the right time,
because I when ibm ibm was not going to say they were the juggernaut
in the commuting industry.
So they said, hey, this is the way it's going to be.
This is the language we're going to use.
Everyone said that ibm says that's what I do.
When oracle was there, we say, hey, we already support sequel.
We're going to go.
Ingress had its own programming language called quell.
That strong breaker still claims is better than sql.
They eventually supported sequel,
but it was by the time they added it, it was too late.
So sequel reasonably spelled as seqeul because it's supposed to be
the sequel to quell.
Right?
To play on words,
then they got sued for trademark enrichment,
so then they renamed it to sql and then there was a standard body to figure
out what should be the programming language we use
for relational databases.
And supposedly they were going to use quell,
set a sequel,
but dome breaker didn't like standards bodies and decided not to submit
any paperwork for quell.
So there's this paragraph here from the larry ellison.
Unauthorized biography.
I don't want you to recall it,
but it came out in the late 90s where they basically talked about how they
thought quell was better than sql,
but mike hated standards body.
So he didn't submit anything.
Anyway.
So that's why we end up with a sequel instead of quell.
Does this one on hacker news occasionally see like people say, hey,
i've better the new version of sequel or better version of a sequel.
And they a lot of the things they end up fixing the problems with in sequel
like having the front claws after the select clause like quell.
Already did that in the 70s.
But we ended up with a sequel.
Sorry.
Right?
So oracle basically wins the crown during the 1980s.
There's a bunch of other startups that come along that do relation databases.
Psi based on formics interface,
terror data was a data warehouse tandem got bought by deck.
Basically, the only one that's still thriving today, I would say,
is oracle and db two and thriving is not the right word I all these
like psi based still makes a ton of money.
But again, if you're a new start up a new company,
you wouldn't use it a lot of these systems are still arrayed maintenance mode,
but oracle is being actively loved,
and then same with db two tear data is they're getting crushed by snowflake.
So stone breaker,
he commercialized his ingress,
goes back to berkeley, starts a new day system called postgress.
If you're the one I postgress is called postgres because it's post ingress.
It's the sense that he built after ingress.
And instead of being a relational data system,
he called this thing as an object relational database system.
Because object oriented program was the hot thing in the 1980s.
And this is why they postcards were designed for the very
beginning to be very extensible.
You can have user defined types, user defined functions, and so forth,
because they wanted to borrow some of the ideas of object oriented databases,
which would be the next slide and be able to extend postcards very easily.
Even today, technically,
postcards is an object based on database system.
People mostly ignore this part,
the object part.
Where are we at so far?
1970s, kodaso?
Is there cobalt that the cobalt way to program davis is their glacial model
comes out?
People say hit is the bad idea.
Coda cell is the right way to do it,
especially where some model wins.
And there's all these ways from davis has come out in the 1980s,
early 1980s,
10 years later after that,
then we end up with these object, ordinary databases.
And what i'm saying where people come along every 10 years and say,
I have a better idea.
In the 1980s,
people recognize that if application available is going to use
an object oriented programming language.
Like c plus is the hot thing in the late 1980s,
that there was this impedance mismatch,
where the way the database system represented data as relations did not map
cleanly into how objects or object oriented programming represented data.
So you'd have to write these sql queries that would basically convert rows
into now objects,
sort of nested hierarchies.
And so a bunch of companies said this is kind of stupid.
Would it be distorted the objects directly in the database as objects?
There's a couple of systems, versant objects or 02.
I think mark logic you actually just got bought a few weeks ago,
but they were late 90s.
And so a bunch of these systems don't exist anymore again.
Are there a maintenance mode?
The what killed him was that there was no standard query language you
could use for object oriented databases.
Eventually, they propose oql the object query language,
but nobody supported that.
It was too late.
Basically,
the problem was because you had this tight coupling
between the database system and the programming language.
It made your application less portable.
It wasn't very easy for you to switch to another object oriented database system,
because you were writing to their proprietary api similar to how ims
exposed a proprietor api to their internal data structures.
So now sequel is supposed to be a standard course for basic queries.
You can easily switch them from monday to such another.
Every bidder has the realm of proprietary extensions.
So even though there is a standard,
it isn't,
there isn't a universal standard that everyone follows.
So you can make the same argument about sequel today.
Or m's hide a lot of this.
Here's what it looks like.
Say.
We have a application code.
We want to store student information.
The student has an ida name, an email address,
and then a potential list of phone numbers.
The way you would represent potentially represent this
in a pure relational model,
meaning where there's only scalar values.
You'd have to have a student table,
and then a student phone table.
So that now, if I want in my programming language,
if I want to instantiate this object,
I would have to do a look up where I either first query the the student
and then do a second query to go get all the phone
numbers or do a join and then make sure I throw
away the the redundant student information.
I when I give the result back.
Again, the object oriented basis guy would say this is stupid,
object oriented.
People say this is stupid.
Just store the the nested objects together in a single record.
And now it's only one fetch to the davis as one read call to go bring
this data in.
So the problem with this, though,
is for a simple example,
there's like a 1 to 1 correspondence routine,
a student phone number, and the student sure this is probably fine.
In fact,
in modern relations data systems,
you could store the phone number as an array of strings.
Most systems will support that.
The trouble is now when you go back to that part supplier issue,
if you now start embedding or de normalizing the all the parts
that a supplier supplies and put them into the supplier record,
then I have that problem.
Or if I need an updated field,
I have duplicate information.
My application code needs to make sure all that's in sync.
I I I don't update some of the records, but not all of them.
Doing complex joins,
make sure you have data integrity,
becomes problematic in in this approach.
And i'm saying there's some cases where you do want to store jason.
And again,
there are progress other day systems that will have a jason type.
And the the methods to store jason data in a binary form
efficiently instead of just text.
Mogadi does this, they have their own base on data type.
Postcards have something similar.
Again, a lot of the ideas that were done in these specialized systems.
So these non relational systems have now found their way into relational systems.
All right.
Then the 1990s I called the boring days,
there wasn't any sort of radical change to the harvard landscape
or the workload landscape.
Right?
There wasn't it wasn't like the advent of the cloud or or microcomputers
in the 1980s,
which is like things are going along, things are getting better.
Harbor is getting better, the data sets are getting bigger,
but it wasn't dramatic change.
Right?
So I think the sort of four major events would be
microsoft bought aa copy or license to the sigh of a source code,
forks it, and then they create sql server.
Segal server supports t sequel,
which is their variance sequel that comes from side base,
side base invented t sequel.
At this point again,
segal server is state of the art side base is in maintenance mode.
I don't know how much of the original sideways code is
still a sequel celebrity these days.
They did major rewrites in 2000.
They did major rereads in 1998 and in 2006.
My sequel sort of get there's a guy in these finland
started rewriting or started writing his own data system to replace
m sequel and called it my sequel.
My is the name of his daughter.
He also did marie db that's his other daughter.
Then a a he has a son named max,
and there is max db like he names all his davis after his kids.
Postgres get recently started as an academic project.
Strawburger loved quell in the 1980s when they first started writing it.
It was used 12.
But then in 95,
90 62 grad students took the original academic source code,
and then convert it to make it actually support sql.
And that's why it's called progress ql they might know what
the original programming language process was written in the 1980s.
Let me take a guess.
This is cobalt.
No.
Abby can close it.
Did you take a lisp?
It was the 80s, right?
Cocaine or whatever like.
And then they realized that was a bad idea.
So then they had a compiler convert the lisp into c and compile that.
And then that was a bad idea.
They rewrote everything in c and then sequel light started early 2000.
It's one dude invented this down in north carolina,
richard hip.
He still looked the main program on the senate.
The one thing that did change,
I would say, was not a dramatic change,
is that people started to realize,
I don't just want to use my data system to transactions and ingest new data.
Someone want to start doing analytics,
start extrapolate new information business.
Intelligent decision support has a bunch of different names.
All these systems at the time are all row stores.
And as we know,
running analytical queries on a row store is highly inefficient.
There was this optimization technique called data cubes where you
basically figure like materialized view,
where you pre computed these multi conventional arrays
of different group i's and aggregation and so forth.
And you would pre compete and you run your analytics on those.
Nobody uses data cubes today because column stores so much faster.
But this is how people got by in the 1990s.
So the big game changer, though,
was in 2000s when the internet comes along.
So again, prior to this,
when you think about it who had big databases,
the big bangs, walmart's, right?
The only like the fortune 500 companies had big data as problems.
But when the internet comes along,
it doesn't take that much for a small number of people to put something
on the internet and have a lot of people start using the application
of the website.
And you start generating a lot of traffic and a lot of data,
a lot of users.
Right?
So this was a big change in how people approach databases in the 2000.
But at the time,
all of the sort of the commercial enterprise databases were very heavyweight,
oracle, db two, cyprus, they were very expensive.
And then the open source databases that we think about today,
postcards and my sql,
they were pretty primitive back in the day.
My sequel to support transactions until inter db came along,
2003 2004.
So what people ended up doing was writing out their own sort
of custom middleware to route queries to these single node database
indices.
So they would sort of treat my sql as like a dumb key value store,
and then have something in front of it to route queries to different shards
that the idea is still widely used today,
but the people were wrong on their own back.
Then.
The other thing that happened was,
again, as I say,
it doesn't take that much to start collecting a lot of data.
More people started wanting to analyze this data.
Then we realize or they realize that the sort
of general purpose data systems at a row store that tries to do
transactions and analytics.
Was that bad idea?
And people started building these custom analytical data systems,
which again,
will be the the sort of key idea that we're focusing on this semester.
A lot of these were distributed and shared nothing of us.
All of these were going to be actually all
of these were relational and sql most of them are forks of post graphs.
And they're going to store the database as column stores.
Again, seems like an obvious idea now.
And because the wind you get from are so significant,
back then this was unheard of,
It's not unheard of it, because the ideas from the 70s,
but like having these explicitly stored,
the ideas columns that was novel,
that was a game changer.
So the sort of the main systems at this time are listed here.
So natzisa was a fork a postgrasse,
but they put a fpga down to the storage layer to make it run filters faster.
Park sells a fork of postcards,
distributed version postgres.
This is actually what redshift is redshift.
They bought a license to park cell.
Didn't really make any changes, just slapped it up and called it redshift.
Was that this is not a secret.
I was telling you, all right, this is public.
And so just threw it up.
It made so much money.
Now we've got to start making this real.
Right?
And it's been written many times over vertica.
That's a company that started by my advisers,
mike stone breaker, and then santa zonatic.
That's a fork, a postgres.
Data leg row was a shorter version of ingress.
And the green plum is a fork and postgres mode adb was
exactly the other one here that was written from scratch.
And that came out of cwi the same.
Have you ever heard of ducky b it's the same research group that made
mode adb dot db was originally called mode db light.
It was a fork mode db to run embedded in like our programs.
And then they rewrote it and ended up being doug db i'm not sure I
may have to bleed this.
I'm not sure this is public.
Microsoft bought data, microsoft bought data, leg grow,
ibm bought the teaser park sell.
They can never get bought that.
He's got and i'm getting licensed.
I think the company's dead vertica got acquired by hp any of you
got never bought and then green palm got bought by
no emc hold on.
At some point, there were miemc it's hard to keep track of this.
They got bought.
And then they divested it off to an emc in order to take back.
Emc had a database piece.
Vmr had a database piece.
They took it out, and they formed a new company called pivotal.
It was green palm and then sequel fire or gem fire,
which I think that notes emc bought them,
vm ware bought sql file.
They took them out, made pivotal,
and then bmr bought pivotal.
It's so data leg row got up with microsoft.
It was a hacked up version of charted ingress.
And I think they paid money for it.
And then after they bought it,
so after they wrote the check,
then they had their technical people actually look at it and say this is
all crap.
We can't use any of this and they threw it all away.
They made them they end up running the sequel server data warehouse
from scratch the parallel data warehouse instead of using any
of these garbage.
There's another one too.
I'm missing astor data they were bought by.
They were bought, I think by terror data.
The while all this work is happening on these parallel column store data warehouses,
there was this other big trend of these matte reduced systems.
Again,
so what it's been 10 years now since the object ordinary databases were
a bad idea,
now we're 10 years later, so this thing comes along from google.
They built a custom execution engine with this map,
reduce programming model that to help them crawl their to build the index
for the web crawl.
And they end up using for a bunch of other data processing tasks
or analytical tasks.
So google put out the paper,
say, hey, that's what we're using.
The pi still happens now,
but google was really the super hot thing in the 2000s.
Right?
Anything they did, any paper they put out,
people did end up go and re implement themselves,
because they thought google is making a ton of money,
because they have all these custom systems.
Let's go build our own custom system too.
Right?
Like h base is a clone a big table,
cause cassandra is a clone a big table and dynamo db that's the acfs dude
was the clone of matt reduce.
So google put that map reduce paper.
Yahoo says, see, that says a good idea.
We can use it too.
They wrote their own open source version called duke.
And the basic idea was that you'd write these user defined functions
like a map and reduce a shuffle phase cover later on next class.
Instead of using a sequel, you'd write these custom functions.
And you just submit them to the davis to the map reduce or do framework
and run them for you.
It takes us back to the 1970s where the programmer had to define what
the data model actually was or the data they were processing.
There's no sequel at the time of these systems.
You had to literally write all parts,
the i'm going to parse this csv file,
and I expect them to have these columns.
And you would write that explicit citations in your in the program encoder
in these functions.
So this was the hot thing in the late 2000.
That was like this is the way to do this.
You ought to add up.
And then stone breaker,
and then this other guy who does invented a lot of the first pillow databases,
put out an article that said this is a bad idea.
Then ii wrote a paper at them and showed it was.
And then people eventually realize it, turns out the old guys are right.
This is a bad idea.
So then they try to put sequel on top of map,
reduce facebook invented hive.
And there's a thing called map rdb at a map r which I I think they're dead now.
But then it turned out that was super inefficient and super slow,
because the way just sort of the way her dude was actually implemented,
or I don't know exactly how the map arts framework actually worked,
but the way they were sort of storing these checkpoints
at every single stage of the query was super inefficient.
And so all this got thrown away.
I i've still exists.
But like people realize a this is actually a bad idea.
As a you want a parallel to the warehouse,
you want the thing that we were shown before.
But it again took 10 years for people to realize this.
This was a bad idea.
Also related to, I won't say bad ideas here too,
but there was this no sequel movement again,
I think brought upon by google and the big table paper basically said,
hey, the the racial model is bad.
The sequel is too slow for modern web application.
We don't need transactions, we don't need joints.
We want to build these systems from scratch,
right?
Because you have to understand like if you're building a website,
you want to think up 2047 a in a database systems transactions that
maybe didn't have
backups or replicas for high availability.
That means if no goes down,
if your whole website goes down, that's bad, you lose money.
So the no sequel guys facing said, well,
maybe you were to let the system maybe have corrupt data
or not strictly follow transaction semantics,
transport in exchange for always being up, always being online.
So there's a bunch of these systems that got built.
Under this model,
some things sometimes is dynamite.
Db was built by amazon for the shopping cart.
If I put some in my shopping cart, it maybe disappears.
This is the end of the world,
probably not.
If I put something in my bank account and disappears, that's a big problem.
Right?
So all these systems basically follow different looser semantics over what
the traditional relational transaction,
strongly consistent daily systems would follow to varying degrees of success.
And as I said before,
basically everybody supports segal now, except for retis,
I think raven db they all have their own version of sql
but it's basically sql without wanting to say it react as dead.
So there I don't I don't think we have any and then oracle new sequel I
think it's just perfectly to be under the covers at the same time.
All right, so soon after the no sequel databases got popular,
there was another movement called new sequel.
This one I was involved in where the idea was that you wouldn't have
the same high scalability and performance of a no sql database system.
But without giving up transactions,
obviously, you can't,
you can't go faster than the speed of light.
So if you have machines in different areas of the world,
you can't make that go faster,
but you at least make sure that things are correct.
So all the systems that came out under this no segal movement,
with maybe the exception of of odb map c will get renamed to a sequel store,
and they wouldn't necessarily call themselves a new sql system now.
And then spanner did detail.
Spanner is still here.
Spanner is legit.
But for the most part,
bunch of things you've never heard of before the trans lattice,
i'm sure nobody's heard of gddb they all pretty much failed.
Foundation db had a sequel there that was kind of crap.
Apple bought down, threw that away.
And they since open source it,
but it's not used as a relational data system with sequel.
Now.
What did happen though?
All a bunch of these systems didn't pan out.
The new transaction data systems aren't actually getting some traction,
and these sort of fall under the umbrella of distributed sequel.
Instead of calling new sql was sort of vague,
you say it's a derivative sql system.
Tide eb is out of china.
Cochrane eb is probably raised the most money of all these.
And then you go by as another startup that's based on postgraduate.
The com, db two was built by, I think, bloomberg.
I've never heard anybody use the com db two outside of bloomberg,
but it is absurd, so it doesn't exist.
So the main take away here is that these systems,
these systems are going against the conventional wisdom that like you want
an original model,
you want to sequel one in transactions.
Because all the new sequel systems are hot.
By the time that people realized I do want sequel, I do want transactions,
they failed or didn't pan out.
Then these systems were the right place at the right time building
off the things that the earlier systems had done finishing up.
We have cloud systems.
Again, we'll cover this a lot throughout the semester.
Basically, now the harbor that escape has changed.
People are no longer running on pram.
You're now running in a cloud,
right?
And that means your resources can be elastic.
You don't have to go through this long provisioning cycle of like,
I want to buy these machines and procurement,
and it takes a long time to actually get them.
With a credit card.
You can spit up a new instance very, very quickly.
So every initially there was a bunch of these databases
of service products or offerings where it would just take
like off the shelf I sequel rather than avm for you.
It's before containers rather than avm for you,
and they charge you for that.
But it didn't.
My sequel wasn't really aware that it's running in the cloud.
It's just running on some vm but since then,
there's now assessments designed from scratch explicitly for running a a
in a cloud system.
But we would call these cloud native snowflakes,
probably the most fame in one of all these like they designed
explicitly in the beginning,
not to run on pram, only to run in the cloud.
Then therefore,
you can make certain design choices which will cover next week.
That can take advantage of that.
Want to make things also to that.
Came out of the map produced world plus now with the cloud.
Are these shared disk systems?
Prior to this,
the the conventional wisdom of how you would build it and tribute
a daily system is would be shared nothing.
Now with the cloud where amazon or whoever is taking care
of the storage layer for you,
you don't want to be able to share nothing system.
You want to use a shared disk system and let the cloud vendor handle
the storage for you.
So there's a bunch of systems now built on top of this shared disk approach.
This is the fact,
this is how everyone's building modern data systems today.
People talk about I have a data lake,
right?
Or we'll see this.
When we talk about data bricks,
they're talking about basically serving on s three, right?
Something with a shared disk model.
Every year I I got to complain about this.
We're at the sort of phase now where it's, again, no sql,
the no sequel women died out.
People realize sequel is the way to go still coming along.
I wouldn't necessarily maybe not necessarily call these new sequel systems,
but they've definitely become more prominent in the last 5 or 6 years
Or these graph database systems.
But the idea is that instead of storing your database as relations,
it's intrinsically, it's a graph.
Let me sort it as a graph structure between relations and so forth.
And this can be either rdf or triple store or property graphs.
It has a bunch of different names.
But it's essentially the same thing that they were doing back in the 70s
with the kodaso network model.
So the big claim is that because you're starting a database
as negatively as graphs.
And because you're now exposing a nato graph api you can be
much better than a relational data system.
We've heard that before.
That was the argument for the object oriented databases.
It's the object,
the jason databases,
all these people make the same argument.
And so sure there are some times what you do want to traverse your database
in a sort of native graph way.
But the segal standard is actually adding support for graph queries this year.
And it's based on cipher,
which was invented by by neo for j so they lose that advantage.
Then now what about the argument that if i'm starting things
negatively as a graph is not going to be better than a relational database?
No,
because the paper that came out last week shows that if you built up db you
incorporate some techniques that will help explicitly for graph
workloads.
Like multi wave joins,
which we will cover a later the semester you cannot perform mu for j
by ten x dfoj has raised hundreds of millions of dollars.
Doctor b's like aa small team of people in the netherlands.
They beat them at 10:00X and it's a real system.
It's not just a toy.
I think graph databases.
We've already see this racial model is absorbing ideas from it.
I don't see these systems really replacing the the relation of davis is
in my lifetime.
I should have put a speech on.
Ii made a public bet where in I I made a public bet,
they said in 2020 by 2030,
the graph database market exceeds the racial database market.
I will change my official cmu directory photo to be like so.
I'm sure when he says I love graph databases and I will use that until I
die or get fired from seeing you.
Ii don't see it happening.
All right.
So quickly finish up time series databases.
So these are now newer databases that are designed to store,
telemetry you're collecting or metrics you're collecting from other services,
other devices, and so forth.
It's relational.
There's this notion of explicit time ordering and the data you're generating.
Therefore,
you can design the system to officially take advantage of the domain
you're working in.
You wouldn't want to use these for storing arbitrary data.
If you have this notion of like ticks or events are showing
up with some notion of time,
anyone do range queries based on those times,
you could design a system to be more efficient to do this.
So probably the three main ones would be time scale,
which is using extensions on top of post graphs, which is super cool,
because you get regular tables and post graphs plus the time series ones.
Influx eb is written from scratch.
I think they're third rewrite,
but again,
they're targeting time series of this.
Click house is out of russia.
This is probably when I first learned about click as when you read
the website and all the things that they supported.
It's a lot of techniques we discussed in the class.
It seemed unreal.
This is super state of the art.
The performer summers look amazing.
My impression, though,
is that it is it's not easy to get up and running a there's still a lot
of manual work you have to do,
but ii think this one's going to be aa big player.
And then prometheus is another big effort in this space.
Last one,
block chain devices.
Yes, bit coin.
If you bought bit coin in 2010.
Great.
Thanks.
Congrats.
But like people had made claims that like block chain databases are
under web three or what everyone call it.
This is a radical different way of how you want to build modern applications.
The old way of having these provisioning servers over relational databases
and sequel and whatever all that stupid you want to build on top
of a block chain database to solve all the world's problems.
At the end of the day, what is a block chain?
It's just a log.
They would call a ledger.
It's like, I write ahead log or the pack says log, the state log.
Here's all the events or things that are happening to this day of the deeds.
Then they had these incremental check sums where the check sum
of a new entry in the log depends on the previous entry of the logs
that way.
If you fudge anything below that.
At a previous entry, the check sum doesn't match,
and you don't have the full data.
The technique was invented on merkel treats.
Then now,
since you're assuming you're running in a decentralized distributed environment,
we don't trust the people that are reading right into the database.
You have to use some visiting fault tolerant or bft protocol to come
to consensus to say,
what's the next entry which put in a log I it's it's a lot of cool ideas
and put together an interesting way,
but is this game changer now?
Right?
I've yet to see a use case that everybody has proposed where a block chain
would solve a problem that you could not solve
with a traditional sql database like postgres,
or you have some external external issues you have to resolve through like law,
right?
Or legal matters.
Right?
So I think there's all garbage.
These systems here are explicitly doing block chain with a
in our decentralized model.
This is the logo for podb amazon has the worst logos because it's like,
unless what is it right?
Like it.
Qlqldb is our quantum ledger database.
It's not a block chain database where it's like decentralized,
like amazon, the trust of authority,
like you authenticate amazon,
you don't have to do bfti think they just do two base commit,
but you still get that verifiable ledger with the check sums.
As far as they know,
this is not going anywhere they make way more money on selling,
reselling my sequel and postcards as rds or under aurora.
Again, I at this point when I first saw these devices,
but maybe there's something I convinced this is all crap.
I was able to say there's no inherent data model to a a block chain database.
It's just entries in the log just bytes.
There's some engine above it that has to interpret what those bytes are.
So it could be a key value store,
relationship database.
It doesn't matter.
There's a bunch of other stuff that should be 2020.
So there's a typo.
There's a bunch of other systems,
categories of things we could talk about embedded databases
like sequel light and rock cb and duck
tb those multi modal or multi model databases where like orangu
tv where you try to support graphs and relations and documents
all in a single one.
In the paper you guys read, we talked about harbor acceleration.
Basically people like the the search for like eldorado,
the golden city in south america.
There's been a search for some kind of hardware for databases for the last 40,
50 years.
It never pans out.
People keep trying, but it never works,
but not that it doesn't work.
It's just you it never gets the adoption in the market.
Commodity harbor was always going to win.
I don't think fpg as or gp us are aa big game changer in the space.
Risk five, potentially some interesting stuff.
But where you're going to see hardware accelerates or databases
is only going to be from the cloud vendors like google,
amazon, and microsoft, because it at their scale,
they can justify paying $50 million in development to build up new custom hardware,
because they're going to make so much money and be more efficient for.
There are millions of customers.
It's very hard to be.
I think it'd be very hard for independent software vendor,
independent hardware vendor to break into that market,
because either because not only had the design to chip or whatever
the hardware accelerator is,
they didn't got to go convince some other software company to put it
in their database.
And it never happens.
We didn't really talk about array matrix,
and the vector data sets the new buzzword now.
Because of machine learning,
there's much of these new nearest neighbor search on vector vectors in new database.
These have been around for a while,
but the vector ones are new.
I would say this is the only,
as far as I know for now,
this is the only type of data you wouldn't actually want to use
a relational database system for where you want to use
a specialized system explicitly designed for vectors.
Because when you think about it, what if it's a multinational array,
you've got to go traverse it,
maybe row wise and column wise and in different dimensions,
and storing that in a table with index columns is a bad idea.
So I think we'll see whether the market is big enough to justify needing
a specialized system.
At this point, the answer is no, as I say, in the paper,
because is there does amazon or microsoft or google offer a vector database
as a service?
No.
They could build one.
They have unlimited money,
but they don't see there being aa large market yet.
So I think it's still too early, but I think this could be the next thing.
Right?
And a there's a ton of these logos.
It's hard to keep track.
I clicked.
All right.
What's going to happen in the future?
So I think right now we're in the golden era databases,
meaning like there's so many different choices, open source,
commercial cloud systems on pram.
Sequel is considered the way to go forward right now.
Again, that'll change in 10 years,
but we'll be back again.
An example would be all the new sql systems for 10 years ago,
except for retis.
I've either died,
or they support sql and something that looks like the rational model.
It's like1+1 equals 2 that basic arithmetic from thousands of years ago.
It stands the test of time because it's the right way to do this.
That's what I sort of see the relational model.
Now sequel the best query language you could have
for a relational database system.
No.
There's obviously problems with it.
But at this. there's so much buy and there's so much existing tooling
and utilities that assume the sql database system.
It would be very hard for anybody to change that.
Right?
I there's so much fracturing in sequel itself,
how you come along say I have a new query language,
then everyone's going to start using it.
Yeah, you could build your one system that does it,
but then nobody else is going to use it.
So I don't know where sql is going to go with the future other than barring
ideas from other non sql systems.
But I see the relational model being standing the test of time.
In my opinion.
There's a reason why ted kahn won the touring world war.
Charles bachman won the turing wood for kodasal.
First,
the both days, it doesn't matter.
All right.
So next class,
I got to go deal with some courts in seattle.
Next week will be not in person.
I'll post the monday lecture and wednesday lecture on youtube.
But we'll kick off starting talking about modern medical daily systems.
And we'll read about the papers about snowflake.
It's from the snowflake people.
There's some details about snowflake,
but I really want to understand the big idea of like running
on a shared disk architecture in the cloud.
Make sure you submit your first reading of you
before the class on2 o'clock wednesday,
right?
I what did I say?
No, there's no reading reviews.
No, there is a did I say tuesday?
No, I i'm just confused.
Make sure you spend your first reading for you.
Monday.
Awesome, guys.
Thank you.
See you.
Ha, that's my favorite all that.
What is it?
It's the st cricket,
idesi make a mess unless I can do it like ago ice cube with the g to the e
to the t here comes duke.
I play the game.
Where's no roof?
And poem is on the custody.
I'm a focus on drink fruit.
Put the bus a cap on the eyes, bro, push.
We gonna go with a blow to the eyes.
Indeed, that's me rolling with 5th one,
south park and south central g and thank us when I party.
By the 12 pack case on the 46 pack,
48 gets the real price.
I drink fruit which are drinking about 12 hours,
they say bill makes you fat,
but saying eyes is straight,
so it really don't matter.